<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://tohab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-09T17:27:50+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rohan Prasad</title><subtitle>A place where Rohan publishes his writings and artwork. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">2025-01 Semiannual update</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-semi-annual-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2025-01 Semiannual update"/><published>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-semi-annual-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-semi-annual-update/"><![CDATA[<p>It is that time of year! Some people send Christmas cards, I send this blog post :D.</p> <p>In 2024, I wrapped up teaching in Taiwan, and said goodbye to all my friends there in May. Then, I went backpacking through Southeast Asia for about five months. Eventually, at the end of October I flew to California, stayed for a couple weeks in the Bay Area, and then onto my parents’ home in Florida where I’ve been for a couple months.</p> <p>I have a newly designed website! Let me know if you have parts you like or suggestions for improvements.</p> <p><strong>Leaving Taiwan &amp; Backpacking</strong></p> <p>Backpacking for five months was no joke. It was a good growth experience, and a good way of understanding myself – consider it a very active form of therapy.</p> <p>Here are some posts about…</p> <ul> <li>*<a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-04-kindness-on-april-23rd-2024/">Kindness on April 23rd, 2024*</a>. In my last couple weeks of teaching, I wrote in appreciation of all the kind people I have known in Taiwan. “Some downbeats last a lifetime.” – Ben Goldberg</li> <li>Joining a <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-04-taiwan-rainbow-gathering-2024/">Rainbow Gathering</a> in Taiwan with hippies in the woods</li> <li>Visiting <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-05-homg-kong/">Hong Kong</a>, <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-05-auroville/">Auroville</a> (an intentional community in South India), <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-06-indian-independence/">traveling independently in India</a></li> <li>Speaking to <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-07-one-month-in-china/">people in China</a>. I stayed there for five weeks in total, traveling with various friends from California and also solo.</li> <li>I also traveled in Thailand, Laos, and Vietnam with my good buddy Dean for about two months. Much of this time was focused on internal change and observation. Dean wrote <a href="https://open.substack.com/pub/urbananimal/p/the-philosophy-paper-that-haunted?r=b6zju&amp;utm_medium=ios">a great reflection</a> about what he learned.</li> <li><a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/">Lessons from Travel</a>. A good post about all that I learned.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Moving Back</strong></p> <p>It was strange moving back… kind of like being an astronaut in outer space, and crash landing back on earth. When I first came back, it was jarring to see other human beings and feel the force of gravity. My body has slightly adjusted.</p> <ul> <li>A post about being <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-11-reverse-culture-shock/">fresh off the boat</a></li> <li>Readjusting <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-11-speaking-plainly/">the way people talk</a> in California</li> <li><a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/">The morning after</a> the 2024 presidential election</li> </ul> <p><strong>Settling in</strong></p> <p>I’ve been in the US about two months since coming back. At some point I realized I ought to start looking for work. This task loomed over my head while traveling, but I honestly wasn’t in the head space to start networking or sending applications out while on overnight buses in Vietnam. Anyway, life is long, and I think it’s okay to take things slowly.</p> <p>It’s a strange thing to think about work while the nature of work is changing so rapidly. I’ve been startled by generative AI, so I wrote a blog post consolidating <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2025/2025-01-the-future-of-work/">my thoughts</a> on how life will change in the next few years.</p> <p>Job hunting for me has three major challenges:</p> <ul> <li>Discovering what I want to pursue. I’ve made progress on this (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2025/2025-01-tangible-and-intangible-progress/">Tangible and Intangible Progress</a>)</li> <li>Pursuing it with maximum efficiency. I haven’t done this yet, but I read a good book about it (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/">Bible-pusher Rohan</a>). The rate of change of the rate of change is positive.</li> <li>Keeping spirits up during the process. Sarasota, Florida has a fantastic ping pong club which I’ve been attending regularly (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/blog/2025/2025-01-miros-ping-pong-advice/">Miro’s Ping Pong Advice</a>). I also have been playing saxophone, designing this website, and hanging out with my dear parents.</li> </ul> <p>That’s all for now! May you be well, joyful, and kind.</p> <p>Rohan</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><category term="update"/><category term="travel"/><category term="identity"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is that time of year! Some people send Christmas cards, I send this blog post :D.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Miro’s Ping Pong Advice</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-miros-ping-pong-advice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Miro’s Ping Pong Advice"/><published>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-miros-ping-pong-advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-miros-ping-pong-advice/"><![CDATA[<p>Miro was an Egyptian table tennis national team player back in his heyday. So he really knows how to <em>play</em>. His advice:</p> <p>“Rohan, this sport is all about practice. If you practice, you will get better, whether you like it or not. Practice. Play with all sorts of people with different styles. If you want to fix problems, come to me… but know that nothing comes quickly. There is no magic in ping pong. Just keep playing.”</p> <p>Miro is over seventy now, and he had a forty-year break from ping pong. But he still comes back to play. When I’m partners with someone in ping pong, I apologize a lot for missing shots. But Miro says, “Don’t be sorry. You play beautifully.” I do make beautiful shots. I know that cognitively, but not deep-down. Because when I play ping pong, I focus on the one in ten shots missed, not the nine out of ten shots made.</p> <p>I played doubles with Miro and a woman named Lynn. Lynn is competitive; she’s the type of person who will look like she wants to throw her racket down when she misses a shot. In watching Lynn, I feel the ridiculousness of my own rage. I too have such feelings, like the anger and self-flagellation of missing a crucial serve.</p> <p>I remember talking something similar with my friends Leon and Alicia. We talked about how during a “performance,” the feeling of tension and stress can be overwhelming. But the reason I play ping, and the reason Leon said he plays piano, is for the joy of the art-form itself.</p> <p>But such anger is self-defeating and egotistical. To play well, you must have your wits about you. And you must enjoy it (the key word is <em>play</em>). I reflect that changing how I react to my emotional impulses and changing how I react to a bouncing ping pong are similarly difficult. Such change happens slowly, bit by bit, not all at once. Patience. I learned this Chinese proverb lately:</p> <p><em>It’s easy to change mountains and rivers, but hard to change a person’s nature. 江山易改 本性難移.</em></p> <p>Okay, my final thought. Roger Federer did a commencement speech at Dartmouth last spring. He shared an interesting statistic. In the height of his prowess as world champion, he won 80% of his matches. But in all those matches, he only won 54% of the points. He reflects on two take-away lessons:</p> <ol> <li>Four percent can be the difference between great and average.</li> <li>Even the greatest tennis player in the world loses 46% of points. He too has to learn to move on gracefully from failure.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ping pong"/><category term="personal"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Miro was an Egyptian table tennis national team player back in his heyday. So he really knows how to play. His advice:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tangible and Intangible Progress</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-tangible-and-intangible-progress/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tangible and Intangible Progress"/><published>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-tangible-and-intangible-progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-tangible-and-intangible-progress/"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a job hunt now, some of my friends ask me how it’s going. Needless to say this is a rather stress-inducing question – one that for the most part, I prefer not to talk about. Unless the other person has some actionable help they can provide, or I value their emotional support. For the most part this is not the case; people ask about the job search flippantly, as if they’re just “checking in”. Of course, some people can provide resources or connections. Some people have great advice for mental fortitude – so it’s not all bad.</p> <p>One reason that “how’s it going” is a hard question to answer is because progress is a multi-faceted thing to measure.</p> <p><strong>Tangible progress.</strong> This is what people typically expect when they ask me about the job search. In their head, the process goes like this:</p> <ul> <li>Decide what you want to do -&gt; Apply like crazy -&gt; Land interviews with whoever gets back -&gt; Choose the least bad of those options</li> </ul> <p>I’m not gonna make some bold claims about how that’s the wrong way to think about things, and I’m not going to suggest some competing framework that is miles better.</p> <p>But do want to share about the <strong>intangible progress</strong>. I’ve made some of this, here’s what it looks like:</p> <ul> <li>Survey knowledge. Learning about an industry, the different companies around, the types of roles available. It’s hard to “measure” how much knowledge you’ve gained in a certain area, and harder still to distill it to a friend or stranger at a moment’s notice.</li> <li>Self-understanding. After learning about what is out there, there’s the question of, “what do I want to do?” This question does not have a simple solution, like the equation x + 5 = 7. If it did, then I would’ve solved this years ago in Algebra 1 (believe me). Self-understanding comes over time, over many conversations, slowly. And the process is never quite complete. I may get a job and find it doesn’t quite fit me. The process of self-understanding continues throughout your life. My parents, who worked for decades and are now retired, face the challenge of self-understanding. There’s a number of ways you can fill your time when retired – it is genuinely hard to contemplate what <em>you</em> really want to do.</li> <li>Conviction. Garnering conviction is the process of developing motivation to proceed along a certain path. If on Day 1 you are very unsure what to do, but you have an inkling that Option A is the one you want to proceed with; then on Day 30, you may have found more and more things about Option A that excite you. You may also speak the lingo of Option A, and know how it compares to Option B and C. Again, it’s hard to quantify how much conviction you have for a certain direction. And it’s something that comes in waves.</li> </ul> <p>Writing this out like I just did, it occurs to me that this progress is real stuff. There is real research and decision-making that has to be done to pursue an intentional career change. It takes contemplation and reflection. But I fear when people ask about my job search, they’re not quite ready for a spiritual journey. Or maybe they are! And I should just prep them better. To steel-man my case for intangible progress, here are some other ways it counts:</p> <ul> <li>Startups. Startups spend plenty of time assembling a time, picking a direction and assessing the market before they start earning revenue. That period of building, testing, and experimenting is key. An example is Meta: when they were just Facebook, they went many years before they had any idea of how to monetize their platform. Focusing on results too early can harm the business in the long-term.</li> <li>Book writers. Consider the task of writing a fantasy novel like Harry Potter. The premise and world-building is essential to that story’s success (my thinking for this is that JK Rowling books following Harry Potter pale in comparison). Arguably, most of the important work for Harry Potter happened before she even wrote the first page.</li> <li>AI compute overhangs. ChatGPT was released in 2022, but the technology actually been possible for maybe 8-10 years before that. In 2016, tons of <em>intangible progress</em> had been made on artificial intelligence. It was illegible to the general public how amazing these capabilities were, which is why ChatGPT came to be seen as such a breakthrough.</li> </ul> <p>Steve Dalton describes this phenomenon in the 2-hour job search. He says that while we know 85% of jobs are gotten through networking, people feel pressured to <em>look like</em> they’re working hard on the job search. And that means essentially wasting time sending apps through job board portals. Building a network and having conversations with people doesn’t necessarily make quantifiable, linear progress towards your goal, but it is the research-supported method for finding a job.</p> <p>(If you’re then going to ask me “how many conversations have you had this week?” please just don’t. It’s annoying and unhelpful. Most people don’t want to be asked about work, because they think about it already so much. So don’t ask unless they bring it up.)</p> <p>Now, I’m not saying tangible progress doesn’t matter. I’d certainly love to have a slew of interviews and job offers my way. But realistically, that won’t happen unless I’m committed to a career goal and ready to make it happen. Like many things, you can go too far the other way – and I also don’t want to be lounging around “contemplating” for months on end. But frankly, my personality is too stressy to ever do that.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="personal"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a job hunt now, some of my friends ask me how it’s going. Needless to say this is a rather stress-inducing question – one that for the most part, I prefer not to talk about. Unless the other person has some actionable help they can provide, or I value their emotional support. For the most part this is not the case; people ask about the job search flippantly, as if they’re just “checking in”. Of course, some people can provide resources or connections. Some people have great advice for mental fortitude – so it’s not all bad.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The future of work, as I see it</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-the-future-of-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The future of work, as I see it"/><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-the-future-of-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2025-01-the-future-of-work/"><![CDATA[<p>To understand the future of work, it helps to think briefly about the history of work.</p> <ul> <li>in pre-historic times, “work” was hunter-gathering. Searching for food and creating shelters were the equivalents of a day-job. With no laws, kingdoms, or strong institutions, people could work however much they want. Life may have been better in that sense. But the work was hard and dangerous.</li> <li>Agriculture displaced hunter-gathering societies. Agriculture allows you to grow much more food for fewer man-hours. Agriculture existed alongside hunter-gatherer civilizations (for instance, in North America, the Aztec civilization fluorished in modern-day Mexico, while the Native American tribes continued in the modern-day US). The agricultural revolution arguably resulted in a dis-improvement the quality of people’s lives. Work became monotonous, boring, and it enabled a more stratified society. At the same time, agricultural societies allowed people to specialize in labor. With smaller numbers of people tending to food production, others could focus on science, technology, governance etc.</li> <li>The industrial revolution was the next major change in production. Machines and assembly lines got so good, that hand-crafted goods were made uneconomical. Whereas agriculture allowed for mass production of food, the industrial revolution allowed for mass production of almost everything else: cars, clothes, human capital (the modern-day education system is a product of Victorian English education system). <ul> <li>Societies that underwent the industrial revolution certainly had the edge. They could create guns and weapons, expand empires. So in a sense, you could avoid industrialization, but only for a time. There were some benefits to everyday people, like cheaper clothes or whatever.</li> <li>The industrial revolution certainly had negative consequences: <ul> <li>Carbon emissions began in earnest</li> <li>Labor exploitation of children and adults</li> <li>Increasing concentration of wealth to owners of capital. Hence, Karl Marx wrote his seminal work <em>Capital</em>.</li> <li>The cruel, abhorrent industrial-scale abuse of animals.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Many people across the world now still work in factories or some form of blue-collar work. So these issues are very still present.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Throughout these revolutions, we see a pattern of certain forms of labor displacing others. Work in agricultural societies replace work in hunter-gatherer times. Work after the industrial revolution replaced work before that. But throughout all of it, work and jobs still exist.</p> <p>Now, the present. We are living through a period of rapid technological change.</p> <p>Let’s say for argument’s sake that the present era started with the invention of the computer. Since then, there’s been a variety of major transformations in global society: - computers &amp; robots making processes more efficient. Right now, computers don’t <em>do</em> much for you, but they make many things you want to do much faster. Hence, almost every job in service-based economies is mediated by computers. - extremely low cost of communication &amp; information. The internet allowed people to learn almost anything online, and communicate with almost anyone. There’s some good consequences (Wikipedia, Khan Academy, educational YouTube) and some bad (social media, polarization, misinformation). - the wide-scale availability of mobile computers (smart phones). So computers are not just used in our work lives, but our personal lives too.</p> <p>And lastly, the major development of the post-computer era is artificial intelligence. By that I mean a system capable of doing “thinking” in some sense of the word. Thinking with logic and reason is what defined the Enlightenment Era, and what separates us from non-human animals. Artificial intelligence, however, could change the status quo. It could mean that very soon, we won’t be the best thinkers on this planet. In short, artificial intelligence threatens to supplant human <em>cognitive labor</em>. This is what underpins my predictions for the short, medium and long-term future.</p> <p>In the short-term…</p> <ul> <li>Generative artificial intelligence (GenAI) will gradually get integrated into tools that we already use. Google docs, google sheets, software development, medical diagnosis. <ul> <li>In some industries, like software or business operations, this will happen very quickly.</li> <li>In industries with greater inertia – licenses, government regulation – it will happen slower. For example, governments, non-profits, law, medicine are all fields where there is less incentive to change.</li> </ul> </li> <li>In time, even the best doctors, lawyers and accounts will start to use GenAI. It saves so much time and provides such a competitive advantage, you simply must. Those who don’t will be dinosaurs within months or years. But it won’t happen overnight. ChatGPT 3 came out over two years ago. But it has barely been integrated into most people’s day-to-day lives – even computer software! It feels as if this integration should happen overnight. But in reality, it doesn’t, even for transformational technologies.</li> <li>I think this stage started in late-2022 with the release of ChatGPT.</li> </ul> <p>In the medium-term:</p> <ul> <li>GenAI will do any and all job functions that require pure thinking. I’m talking accounting, law, programming, theoretical research.</li> <li>What is left for humans in this future? Plenty. Cognitive labor is only one part of most jobs in developed economies. Humans would then be better suited for: <ul> <li>emotional labor. Politics, activism, sales – anything that involves persuasion. Also, care-taking, nurturing, coaching, therapy. If you take a therapist, for instance, while the AI may provide great resources intellectually, humans have some advantage in being physically present for others. We also can hype ideas up and motivate others.</li> <li>physical labor. Fixing bulbs, doing factory work, taking care of children and the elderly all involves physical labor. Teaching young kids, like I did, is partially a cognitive task, but mostly a job that requires emotional skills and physical presence.</li> <li>capital allocation and risk. CEOs, professors etc. may not do direct work themselves, but they allocate capital and therefore are responsible when things fail. More and more jobs will look like this. You may outsource work to an AI, but you’re still responsible for the outcomes.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What is work like in this world? <ul> <li>For me, it’s exciting and liberating to be freed from mind-numbing cognitive labor. Those with people-skills and the abilities to effectively use AI will benefit. Those that can’t transition may have trouble.</li> <li>The intelligence offered by AI is only useful if you work a white-collar job. What if you work in the hinterlands of America – mining or factory towns? What if you work in a shoe factory in Vietnam? Sadly, AI is not going to liberate anyone from those jobs. At least, if we confine ourselves to cognitive general intelligence.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Some predict we will reach this level of artificial super intelligence (intelligence that exceeds the best of humans) by 2027. But I still think it will take years or decades for GenAI to truly seep into every industry in every country across the globe (just like it took decades for electrification to be truly ubiquitous).</li> </ul> <p>In the long-term:</p> <ul> <li>What can the AI given enough time? <ul> <li>Embodied AI (ie. humanoid robots) can do <em>any</em> job (physical, cognitive, emotional) that a human can. Probably better, cheaper and faster.</li> <li>AI will design and conduct full-on scientific experiments, advancing the state of the art in R&amp;D and manufacturing.</li> <li>AI will run governments – ideally optimizing for human and animal welfare.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What’s left for humans? <ul> <li>In this theoretical world, humans would be left to do jobs that have essentially no function in society. Everyone would just be like a retiree in Florida – killing time on the golf course, in painting class, and at dinner parties.</li> <li>Realistically, there would be work to do, chiefly in politics. Who’s to say which AI system we should put our faith in? What values should the AI be optimizing for?</li> <li>We’ve had steadily increasing average incomes for decades, but poverty has not gone away, and many curable diseases take lives every year. These are not technological problems – they are political. Work would be there to distribute the benefits of AI across the world, and orient the AI so it benefits the climate and animals.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What about work? <ul> <li>Right now, there is enough wealth in the world for <em>everyone</em> to have ample food, shelter, and medical care. Yet that is not how the world operates. It has been the case for hundreds of years that you need to “work” to live (in the US, at least). We should expect the status quo to continue, no matter how dramatic the changes are in technology. For a work-free future, major political activism has to happen to create a 4-day work week etc. Or you can move to other countries where such futures are closer to reality.</li> <li>That said, work would hopefully be more enjoyable. It may just involve making art, playing live music, or organizing humanoid robots to do your bidding. There may be “work” to be done in colonizing the stars, melding our minds with machines, etc. Who knows?</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>So those are my predictions for the long-run. But let’s not forget the relevant Keynes quote, “in the long-run, we’re all dead.” In this case, we may be dead because of run-away uncontrolled AI. Or alternatively, AI may bring about next Guilded Age with <a href="https://mkorostoff.github.io/1-pixel-wealth/">astronomical wealth</a> inequality, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killing_of_Brian_Thompson">political assassinations</a>and <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/senate/5047584-bernie-sanders-blasts-elon-musk-spending-deal/">tycoons running politics</a>. Who knows?</p> <p>Frankly, the upside of AI is just so great. And anyways, Pandora’s box has already been opened. People have seen what AI is capable of, so there’s no going back. It’s only a question of when. In the meantime, our job is to work on the issues of democratic governance, just allocation of wealth, and rights for all living creatures. The rest should sort out itself.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ethics"/><category term="social-change"/><category term="ai"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To understand the future of work, it helps to think briefly about the history of work. in pre-historic times, “work” was hunter-gathering. Searching for food and creating shelters were the equivalents of a day-job. With no laws, kingdoms, or strong institutions, people could work however much they want. Life may have been better in that sense. But the work was hard and dangerous. Agriculture displaced hunter-gathering societies. Agriculture allows you to grow much more food for fewer man-hours. Agriculture existed alongside hunter-gatherer civilizations (for instance, in North America, the Aztec civilization fluorished in modern-day Mexico, while the Native American tribes continued in the modern-day US). The agricultural revolution arguably resulted in a dis-improvement the quality of people’s lives. Work became monotonous, boring, and it enabled a more stratified society. At the same time, agricultural societies allowed people to specialize in labor. With smaller numbers of people tending to food production, others could focus on science, technology, governance etc. The industrial revolution was the next major change in production. Machines and assembly lines got so good, that hand-crafted goods were made uneconomical. Whereas agriculture allowed for mass production of food, the industrial revolution allowed for mass production of almost everything else: cars, clothes, human capital (the modern-day education system is a product of Victorian English education system). Societies that underwent the industrial revolution certainly had the edge. They could create guns and weapons, expand empires. So in a sense, you could avoid industrialization, but only for a time. There were some benefits to everyday people, like cheaper clothes or whatever. The industrial revolution certainly had negative consequences: Carbon emissions began in earnest Labor exploitation of children and adults Increasing concentration of wealth to owners of capital. Hence, Karl Marx wrote his seminal work Capital. The cruel, abhorrent industrial-scale abuse of animals. Many people across the world now still work in factories or some form of blue-collar work. So these issues are very still present.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan"/><published>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p><strong>Taiwanese sticker culture.</strong> It’s totally normal in Taiwan to send stickers to your friends. And your coworkers, boss, customers – whoever. When I landed in Kaohsiung for the first time, my interactions with the quarantine hotel I was staying at were mediated through LINE, the common messaging app in Taiwan &amp; Japan. Most of the time, I would type something, they would respond, and then send a sticker.So many stickers. A sticker is like a glorified emoji that moves. Or you could see it like sending a meme or a GIF. And you can also buy them. And they make stuffed animals and key-chains based on the common ones.</p> <p>Honestly, I think we need more of this in the West. As I re-acclimatize to American culture, I realize how much warmth and nuance we’re missing out in with the purely textual medium.</p> <p><strong>Hope and change.</strong> What’s something that Obama, Trump, and Bernie all have in common? They acknowledged the struggle of working people in America. Obama’s 2008 campaign, “Change we can believe in.” Bernie in 2016, “Not me, us.” (with messaging about a “political revolution”). And Trump said he would “Make America Great Again” and “drain the swamp”.</p> <p>Trump’s populist messaging struck a chord with the American people, and I hope that the Democrats take note. The Democrats came off this year as out of touch, patronizing, and fake. Yes, sure, maybe sexism and racism had something to do with it. But I think really the problem is lack of authenticity.</p> <p>Trump is authentic. He speaks his mind. He’ll say things other people are afraid to say. Given polls skew towards the Democrats, it seems like there’s a number of shy Republicans out there. Why is that? Trump is also, as it happens, a master of the media. He used two attempted assasination attempts to his great advantage. Apparently, there was some photo of him working at McDonald’s that went viral. He bought the support Elon, who – whether you like it or not – made the Republicans seem a lot cooler. And he chose a convincing, well-spoken vice-presidential candidate to add in the mix.</p> <p>I do think the Democrats needed the 2024 election as a kick in the butt. If the stakes really are as high as they said, then they should be fighting a whole lot smarter. This isn’t just about more campaign dollars. The Presidential election is about picking a phenomenal candidate, and finding a message that *really* clicks with people. I sometimes feel like the Harris campaign was run in a way that made them feel satisfied with the effort they put in, but in actuality wasn’t at all competitive. Now people may disagree.</p> <p>The point is that there’s much we can learn from how the Republicans won the hearts and minds of people across the country. Without this temperature check, would we liberals have any idea how much people are hurting? People are losing their stable jobs, they’re afraid of automation and AI, and the cost of living is going up and up. This happens in fully blue states just as much as it happens in purple or red counties. So something has seriously got to change.</p> <p><strong>Bible-pusher Rohan.</strong> Before I moved to Taiwan, I was fanatical about this book, <em>The Defining Decade</em> by Meg Jay. The lessons of this book are left for another blog post. Certain books like that can really reshape my world-view. That book in particular wasn’t saying anything crazy or marvelous, but rather putting oft-repeated advice in a new perspective – one that I had an easier time digesting. It galvanized me to do something different and original: move to Taiwan and be an English Teacher. My thoughts at the time were would give me “identity capital”: a story, a set of experiences that make me a memorable human being. At the very least, it’s evidence that I can go against the grain, and follow through on something off the beaten path because it makes sense to me.</p> <p>These days, I’ve been thinking about the job search. There’s a whole slew of tips and tricks online, but that doesn’t make the job search any easier. Most of the people I’ve talked to took months to get anywhere. If you think about it, most people have only ever job hunted a few times in their life. Sometimes less. So people’s experience is limited; it is by nature anecdotal. There’s some old parable about the seven blind men that try to draw an elephant. Basically, they each touch different parts of the elephant, but with such a limited scope, they can’t get the whole picture of what the creature looks like.</p> <p>Two years ago, I recommended <em>The Defining Decade</em> to anyone and everyone. Now, I have a new Bible: <em>The 2-Hour Job Search</em> by Steve Dalton. This book is more easily summarized: instead of shooting resume after resume into the black hole of job application portals, your time is better spent networking at targeting companies by informational interviews to learn about your industry. Moreover, Dalton provides explicit instructions on how to implement this strategy. No generic tips &amp; tricks – just actionable advice, based on research and his experience as a career counselor. I like this book because it flips the traditional paradigm on its head. And god, there’s a lot of vague advice for job searching, but very few people who actually know how to do it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="taiwan"/><category term="politics"/><category term="social-change"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the spectrum of agency</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the spectrum of agency"/><published>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>If you were a rich person in the 1800s, would you used cotton shirts made by slave laborers? If you were a German in the 1940s, would you used soap made by the bodies of the victims of the Holocaust? If you were alive in the 2000s, would you have eaten the flesh of dead animals.</p> <p>Agency is how much choice we exert over our lives. The answer to those three questions for most people is maybe not, but probably yes.</p> <p>Humans are designed to go along with the stream of water that is society. We are social creatures, and are generally agreeable. I think so, at least; we are more similar than we are different. If we had too much heterogeneity, there would be more social activists, perhaps, but also more serial killers, racists, and social pariahs. Like birds flying in the sky, moving with your flock is a helpful instinct. Obedience and conformity to social expectations is what lets the world run day-to-day.</p> <p>On the other hand, humans also have an innate capacity for courage, creativity, and uniqueness. These are the qualities that create social disruption, change, and innovation.</p> <p>There’s a balance to be had. Conformity helps build great, stable nations; but too many and we’re on the road to serfdom. Disruption fuels technological progress; but too much and we’re in a land of warlords feuding over power.</p> <p>Social expectations appear in more mild senses too. For instance, the idea that you should stay till the end of a concert instead of leaving halfway through. Good, or bad? Good to respect the performers. Bad because you may be driving yourself crazy. People may come on different sides of this debate, and it’s probably a case by case situation.</p> <p>Here are some other pieces of conventional wisdom:</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.”</li> </ul> <p>These are actually all good pieces of advice, I think. But who’s to say when these rules of thumb get out of hand? Conventional wisdom also told people it’s okay to abuse slaves, slaughter Jews and eat the flesh of animals. For every piece of advice, there’s a counter-adage that might be equally valid.</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.” &lt;–&gt; “There are no wrong notes in jazz.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.” &lt;–&gt; ““Be yourself!”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.” &lt;–&gt; “Be in the moment!”</li> </ul> <p>Vegetarians and animal activists know this conflict intimately. How often have you been invited to eat a piece of meat, and feel like you “should” out of courtesy or politeness – but also feel like you “shouldn’t” perpetuate violence against innocent creatures.</p> <p>It’s up to all of us to decide how much we follow social convention, and how much we exert our own agency. Expressing myself through my choices typically brings me join, and so here are a few ways I like to do it:</p> <ul> <li>Arranging your living environment to be tidier.</li> <li>Choosing to focus on your breath.</li> <li>Brushing your teeth, or flossing to satisfaction.</li> <li>Installing Linux. I did this recently – It brings me great joy. *So* much better than Windows. It feels like I have a whole new computer. And there’s so much more choice and freedom on my laptop, now, which I had very little of on Windows.</li> <li>Wearing clothes you like, or thrifting for nice stuff.</li> <li>Creating art or music without thinking of whether it sounds “good”.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="philosophy"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="social-change"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Travel</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Travel"/><published>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>See many perspectives.</strong> While traveling I met a young Israeli sniper on the beaches of Siargao, Chinese nationalists who argue passionately in defense of the Chinese system, conservative French people who hate social welfare but also use it to travel. Keeping cool, curious, and empathetic is hard when you have different beliefs to someone.</li> <li><strong>Overcome social anxiety.</strong> So often when traveling, asking the nearest person is the best way to get the most accurate information. It’s essentially a necessity to be bold enough to do this. I think I’m relatively good at doing this but I still have reluctance sometimes that doesn’t serve me. Talking to a stranger is a subclass of “jumping into cold water” – doing something you know has to be done, but you dread and keep procrastinating. I can think of many things that induce a similar feeling: quitting a job, packing up your things, breaking up with someone.</li> <li><strong>See different societies and how they differ.</strong> Even between Thailand, Laos, and Vietnam, there were vastly different languages and governmental systems. I learned about Laotian government incompetence; Vietnamese national pride (so many communist flags!); and the laissez-faire Thai labor economy.</li> <li><strong>Learn what is essential to carry.</strong> My friend Dean brought a yoga block (like a styrofoam brick) that he used for meditation and sitting when the ground is uncomfortable. Surprisingly useful! I brought ziploc bags with me to label my things. And a nail clipper. Know thyself.</li> <li><strong>How to make choices with little information.</strong> This is so crucial. So crucial. Where is this bus going? Should I trust this tuk-tuk driver to take me to the ferry port? Why is there a “terminal fee” when I’ve already bought a boat ticket? Will my bag be overweight or just right? Is this vegetarian soup also vegan? So many cases of not knowing the full story – having to go by someone’s word and just laughing along. On the internet and in America we live in a high-information environment. You can look up anything. It is much harder to look up specifics of traveling in certain places abroad (especially in China – that’s like a whole other universe). So we rely on incomplete information. We pray to the travel gods when we have done all we can. We know that things will be okay so long as you have your passport and wallet and your life.</li> <li><strong>How to be kind to people under duress.</strong> Lack of sleep, 14-hour bus journeys, decision fatigue, tired of looking up vegan food. But then it’s always better to be nice to the next person you cross paths with. Patience under fire.</li> <li><strong>How to stay calm.</strong> Deep, slow belly breaths. There’s a book about it.</li> <li><strong>How to get information from people, and know what information sources to trust.</strong> Asking people where they recommend to go in a city. Deducing their vibe, thinking about whether you’ll like what they like. Chumming up with people, appreciating them when they help you out. Knowing people’s love languages – though most of what I give is kind words and hostel fees. Much more art than science.</li> <li><strong>Make plans that are specific but also flexible.</strong> I realized early on that having a hostel booked for at least one night is a good bet. Otherwise, remain flexible!</li> <li><strong>Adjust plans when necessary.</strong></li> <li><strong>Be in touch with your feelings about physical environments and people.</strong> Recognizing when you’re not vibing with a place and want to move on. Recognizing when the crew you’re with is not your crew, and you should kindly excuse yourself.</li> <li><strong>Communicate without a shared language.</strong> Smiles. Pointing. Gesturing. Extensive Google Translate.</li> <li><strong>Express gratitude.</strong> Traveling with just ten kilograms on your back, gratitude is often all you can give.</li> <li><strong>Self-advocate, ask for what you need.</strong> Even when someone’s paid to help you, like a hostel front desk staff, asking for something you need is difficult. And it is tiresome to always be reliant on someone else – but, well, that’s life. I hope one day I can pay this forward, and help others who rely on me.</li> <li><strong>Appreciate where you’re at.</strong> We travel the external world to explore our inner worlds. The most beautiful places can be so difficult if you’re not feeling it. Conversely, the raunchiest places can be hilarious and beautiful if you are appreciating it.</li> <li><strong>Mental endurance, persistence.</strong> All the things I mentioned above are harder when it’s month 3 or 4 of traveling.</li> <li><strong>The courage to go against the grain.</strong> When I was traveling, I had just one good friend, Dean, who was doing so at the same time. Long-term backpacking is not something most people do. The tenacity and courage it takes to do it is substantial. It also takes courage, I say to myself, to not have a job lined up, and hope that things will work out in the end.</li> <li><strong>Make trade-offs: money, comfort, time, safety.</strong> Decisions, decisions. So many of them while traveling. No routines, only moving forward. Exhausting!</li> <li><strong>How to kill time/wait when you need to.</strong> Talking to people. Reading my Kindle. Podcasts.</li> <li><strong>Ground yourself in a new physical environment.</strong> (e.g. via routine, exercise, putting luggage in a certain way). No routines but mini-routines. I had my bags set up so they felt familiar. A place for everything, and everything in its place, my dad likes to say. In the same vein, mini-routines in the morning, or a set time to go foraging for food, or having a hot beverage.</li> <li><strong>Accepting there will be mistakes.</strong> In Hong Kong, I thought it was way too pricey and bought too many groceries. I lost my hat and never went back to look for it. I got overcharged for a train booking. Mistakes are human, and I am human. It is part of life to make missteps, and these missteps do not define you. That’s a tough lesson.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="personal"/><category term="travel"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">blogging in collaboration</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="blogging in collaboration"/><published>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>I want to say that I don’t write blog posts with AI. I say that, while also thinking that there may be good reasons to. And I may try it in the future. Here are some points for using AI and counter-point, too.</p> <p>Point:</p> <ul> <li>When a director “creates” a movie, they do not create it individually. The director provides the creative direction, importantly <em>chooses</em> what goes in the final cut. Yet it is actors, editors, writers and producers that do the day-to-day work to make it happen. I might write a blog post with AI in the same way that a director creates a movie. Doesn’t that have artistic validity?</li> <li>Sometimes something is just a fraction of an idea, but I’d need help/motivation to turn that into a full piece. Oftentimes examples and structure can help flesh out the idea to the reader. For instance, I had an idea, “solo travel is like joining the Jesuits”. I felt like it had legs, but didn’t know enough to really make the argument. AI stepped in in that moment.</li> </ul> <p>Counterpoint:</p> <ul> <li>Using AI to write doesn’t let you practice writing. Why is writing an important skill? It is the intentionality of words, the careful selection of language to put on a piece of paper. Writing is a way to essentialize yourself. Your written work is a textual manifestation of yourself. <ul> <li>Counter-counterpoint: Can’t writers that collaborate with AI have their own personal mark? Directors of movies are assisted, but they have their own distinctive style. I wonder how much artistry and uniqueness there is to ordering about AI in the way that exactly works for you.</li> </ul> </li> <li>It encourages the creation of junk. The author doesn’t have to put in so much effort into creation, and so that which is created is less thought-out. Of course, you can be a thoughtful, careful collaborator with AI so that you only say what you mean. You can also be a thoughtless, careless writer even without AI.</li> <li>It completes your thoughts. Perhaps a continuation of Counterpoint #1. When I’m writing, I’m forced to exactly think what I want to say. It is a certain way of looking at yourself. When AI completes your statements, it may not be an exact reflection of what is on your mind. But you may roll with it anyways. <ul> <li>Additional thought: AI is genuinely a useful thought partner. I can have a discussion with AI and learn a lot. It can take an idea or theory I have and strengthen it greatly. Still, this point stands in the sense that I believe it’s important to have sovereignty over thinking, to have a space where your thought stand independently from external forces.</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="blogging"/><category term="ai"/><category term="technology"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the morning after</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the morning after"/><published>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>The Republicans have taken the Senate, likely the house, and the Presidency. The legislative trifecta allows Trump to be unchallenged in the White House. What do we take from this moment?</p> <p>We cannot run history again. So we will not know the exact combination of factors that led to such a stunning defeat on the Democrats part. That said, we can wager some guesses. Kamala was female, and a black woman. As with all firsts, she needed to be exceptional. Obama met that bar – he defied the odds and won overwhelingly in 2008. Hillary didn’t. Kamala didn’t.</p> <p>What was it about Kamala that threw people off? She was left in a bad position. She had to defend Biden’s administration but also claim to be a departure from it. Her own policy record is wishy-washy. And her own agenda was amorphous. An uninspring economic agenda, no clear stance on immigration. Unconvincing stance on Israel. What geniuses told her to run this way? If this election was truly a fight against fascism, then why didn’t they try harder?</p> <p>Let’s not forget the Democrats unrelenting focus on the Donald. This is a through line between Biden and Harris’s campaigns. The focus was always, always on Donald Trump: the way he was a threat to democracy, a threat to women’s rights, a racist. As we see the results of the popular vote, I have to wonder if this rhetoric is self-defeating. Clearly, a good portion of the country has a great deal of respect for Donald Trump. And still the Democrats beat him over the head with labels. The party with the alleged moral high ground used name-calling and exagerration to fight Trump.</p> <p>This way of talking may alienate even further Trump’s base. Middle-class, working white men are the classic supporters of Donald Trump; the communities described in JD Vance’s A Hillbilly Elegy. Does it work to attack such people? If Joe Biden won on this platform in 2020, I believe it is because of his strong record of a middle of the road politician, and identity as a literal average Joe.</p> <p>Kamala was unknown by most voters before her own campaign, and so would’ve done better to define herself on positive qualities rather than “prosecuting” her opponent. Perhaps these issues could have been fixed if, like Ezra Klein suggests, we had a full-blown primary runoff for the Democratic candidate – a chance to test their nettle, show the stuff they’re made of.</p> <p>America has chosen Trump, and this is the time to find out why.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="politics"/><category term="america"/><category term="social-change"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">judgement</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="judgement"/><published>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>Many people in my life have called me judgmental. The truth is that I speak my mind a lot, and sometimes people don’t like it. Judgement is seen as something that is bad and I’ve never understood this. So this blogpost aims to breakdown the stages of judgement.</p> <p>Let’s say you are a doctor working with a diabetes patient. The patient has been diabetic for a long time, and you notice they continue to eat sugary foods and drinks being told it will lead to more diabetes. That is stage 1 of judgement: observation and evaluation. The doctor observes may predict that the patient will continue to eat sugar if they continue on the current path.</p> <p>Stage 2 is about the doctor’s inner world. What does the doctor think of this person? Do they think they are a bad person? Lazy? Un-attending to their health? The subjective term “lazy” is commonly seen as a negative critique of another person. You are bad, I am good.</p> <p>Stage 3 is about expressing the inner world. Does the doctor give subtle cues that they think the patient is a bad person? Do they tsk tsk when they hear how much Coca Cola the patient has been drinking? Do they directly <em>say</em> the person is lazy, through tone of speech, imply they are bad person?</p> <p>So now let me evaluate what I think of these stages.</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1 of judgement, observation, I believe is a normal, healthy thing for human beings to do. In this case, it is the doctor’s job to have an understanding of the patient and their behaviors. Not making this evaluation would be irresponsible. Even other people in the patient’s life may have noticed their sugar-eating habits. For instance, if you look at someone who is obese, you will know so immediately and you cannot avoid it.</li> <li>Stage 2 of judgement is subjective internal criticism. I believe this is something to be avoided. There are no wrong notes in jazz (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/the-spirit-of-jazz.html">here</a>). If you believe life is a sandbox game, then you should also believe that people are entitled to lead the lives they want to lead. If someone wants to ingest sugar, tobacco, or other drugs, or pursue an unconventional life path, I believe that’s their decision – what you do in life, I believe, is an aesthetic choice. At the same time, I frequently, involuntarily, have internal subjective criticisms of others. It is natural. There are institutions at work that promote certain values over others, and we are but mere mammals socially programmed to uphold social conventions. You cannot control the thoughts you have, but you can control what you do with them.</li> <li>Stage 3 of judgement is sharing. When someone goes to see a doctor, they are probably hoping for the doctor’s objective assessment of how they’re doing in managing diabetes. Insofar as this will be positively received, it’s good. If the person legitimately needs a reminder that they should get back on the train of diabetes for the good of their health, then they will appreciate the doctor’s objective evaluation and take it seriously: something needs to change. However, what if the doctor’s objective evaluation is tinged with subjective criticism? This may in fact add to the strength of the feedback. Like parents forcing their child to practice piano or look both ways when crossing the road. However, there’s a potential issue with sharing negative critique: it isn’t inspiring. It may make the patient stressed and/or strain the relationship with their doctor. They may not want to come back for more visits in the future, in which case sharing internal critiques, even non-verbally, caused more harm than good.</li> </ul> <p>So to reiterate, judgement has three stages:</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1: Objective observation/assessment. Sometimes helpful.</li> <li>Stage 2: Subjective internal criticism. Often harmful.</li> <li>Stage 3: Sharing observations/criticism. A fine line!</li> </ul> <p>Stage 3 is by far the thorniest part of this. Ideally, when you have a beneficial, objective observation of someone, you can share it to their listening ears. But how do you know that when you share your observation, it is not tinged with your subconscious judgement of their behavior? And even if you don’t have subjective internal criticisms, will the other person understand that you are simply trying to share an objective statement? Intent of non-judgement may have a judgmental impact.</p> <p>Those who speak their mind too much are called judgmental, presumptuous, or bigoted. Simultaneously, they have the courage to share personal truths that people may appreciate. A prime example is Donald Trump. He is someone who certainly is bigoted and arrogant and over-shares. And yes, he is also speaking to concerns people have: concerns about crime, immigrants, woke culture. Personally, I am grateful for Trump, because without him we wouldn’t have known about the division that ails this country. Of course, in illuminating this he has spread discord and violence as well.</p> <p>I tell friends I love them dearly, and I tell them that certain behaviors of theirs piss me off beyond belief. I’ve sent letters to teachers and professors telling them how much their class means to mean, and when I feel like their class is meaningless. All the times I am speaking a truth I feel, and to do so is intrinsically good. Yet I realize that such truth must be tempered with compassion and tactful delivery. I don’t pretend I do a good job at this. But, for now, I do what I do and it’s a process of learning.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><category term="philosophy"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry></feed>