<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://tohab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-03T02:05:47+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rohan Prasad</title><subtitle>A place where Rohan publishes his writings and artwork. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan"/><published>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p><strong>Taiwanese sticker culture.</strong> It’s totally normal in Taiwan to send stickers to your friends. And your coworkers, boss, customers – whoever. When I landed in Kaohsiung for the first time, my interactions with the quarantine hotel I was staying at were mediated through LINE, the common messaging app in Taiwan &amp; Japan. Most of the time, I would type something, they would respond, and then send a sticker.So many stickers. A sticker is like a glorified emoji that moves. Or you could see it like sending a meme or a GIF. And you can also buy them. And they make stuffed animals and key-chains based on the common ones.</p> <p>Honestly, I think we need more of this in the West. As I re-acclimatize to American culture, I realize how much warmth and nuance we’re missing out in with the purely textual medium.</p> <p><strong>Hope and change.</strong> What’s something that Obama, Trump, and Bernie all have in common? They acknowledged the struggle of working people in America. Obama’s 2008 campaign, “Change we can believe in.” Bernie in 2016, “Not me, us.” (with messaging about a “political revolution”). And Trump said he would “Make America Great Again” and “drain the swamp”.</p> <p>Trump’s populist messaging struck a chord with the American people, and I hope that the Democrats take note. The Democrats came off this year as out of touch, patronizing, and fake. Yes, sure, maybe sexism and racism had something to do with it. But I think really the problem is lack of authenticity.</p> <p>Trump is authentic. He speaks his mind. He’ll say things other people are afraid to say. Given polls skew towards the Democrats, it seems like there’s a number of shy Republicans out there. Why is that? Trump is also, as it happens, a master of the media. He used two attempted assasination attempts to his great advantage. Apparently, there was some photo of him working at McDonald’s that went viral. He bought the support Elon, who – whether you like it or not – made the Republicans seem a lot cooler. And he chose a convincing, well-spoken vice-presidential candidate to add in the mix.</p> <p>I do think the Democrats needed the 2024 election as a kick in the butt. If the stakes really are as high as they said, then they should be fighting a whole lot smarter. This isn’t just about more campaign dollars. The Presidential election is about picking a phenomenal candidate, and finding a message that *really* clicks with people. I sometimes feel like the Harris campaign was run in a way that made them feel satisfied with the effort they put in, but in actuality wasn’t at all competitive. Now people may disagree.</p> <p>The point is that there’s much we can learn from how the Republicans won the hearts and minds of people across the country. Without this temperature check, would we liberals have any idea how much people are hurting? People are losing their stable jobs, they’re afraid of automation and AI, and the cost of living is going up and up. This happens in fully blue states just as much as it happens in purple or red counties. So something has seriously got to change.</p> <p><strong>Bible-pusher Rohan.</strong> Before I moved to Taiwan, I was fanatical about this book, <em>The Defining Decade</em> by Meg Jay. The lessons of this book are left for another blog post. Certain books like that can really reshape my world-view. That book in particular wasn’t saying anything crazy or marvelous, but rather putting oft-repeated advice in a new perspective – one that I had an easier time digesting. It galvanized me to do something different and original: move to Taiwan and be an English Teacher. My thoughts at the time were would give me “identity capital”: a story, a set of experiences that make me a memorable human being. At the very least, it’s evidence that I can go against the grain, and follow through on something off the beaten path because it makes sense to me.</p> <p>These days, I’ve been thinking about the job search. There’s a whole slew of tips and tricks online, but that doesn’t make the job search any easier. Most of the people I’ve talked to took months to get anywhere. If you think about it, most people have only ever job hunted a few times in their life. Sometimes less. So people’s experience is limited; it is by nature anecdotal. There’s some old parable about the seven blind men that try to draw an elephant. Basically, they each touch different parts of the elephant, but with such a limited scope, they can’t get the whole picture of what the creature looks like.</p> <p>Two years ago, I recommended <em>The Defining Decade</em> to anyone and everyone. Now, I have a new Bible: <em>The 2-Hour Job Search</em> by Steve Dalton. This book is more easily summarized: instead of shooting resume after resume into the black hole of job application portals, your time is better spent networking at targeting companies by informational interviews to learn about your industry. Moreover, Dalton provides explicit instructions on how to implement this strategy. No generic tips &amp; tricks – just actionable advice, based on research and his experience as a career counselor. I like this book because it flips the traditional paradigm on its head. And god, there’s a lot of vague advice for job searching, but very few people who actually know how to do it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the spectrum of agency</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the spectrum of agency"/><published>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>If you were a rich person in the 1800s, would you used cotton shirts made by slave laborers? If you were a German in the 1940s, would you used soap made by the bodies of the victims of the Holocaust? If you were alive in the 2000s, would you have eaten the flesh of dead animals.</p> <p>Agency is how much choice we exert over our lives. The answer to those three questions for most people is maybe not, but probably yes.</p> <p>Humans are designed to go along with the stream of water that is society. We are social creatures, and are generally agreeable. I think so, at least; we are more similar than we are different. If we had too much heterogeneity, there would be more social activists, perhaps, but also more serial killers, racists, and social pariahs. Like birds flying in the sky, moving with your flock is a helpful instinct. Obedience and conformity to social expectations is what lets the world run day-to-day.</p> <p>On the other hand, humans also have an innate capacity for courage, creativity, and uniqueness. These are the qualities that create social disruption, change, and innovation.</p> <p>There’s a balance to be had. Conformity helps build great, stable nations; but too many and we’re on the road to serfdom. Disruption fuels technological progress; but too much and we’re in a land of warlords feuding over power.</p> <p>Social expectations appear in more mild senses too. For instance, the idea that you should stay till the end of a concert instead of leaving halfway through. Good, or bad? Good to respect the performers. Bad because you may be driving yourself crazy. People may come on different sides of this debate, and it’s probably a case by case situation.</p> <p>Here are some other pieces of conventional wisdom:</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.”</li> </ul> <p>These are actually all good pieces of advice, I think. But who’s to say when these rules of thumb get out of hand? Conventional wisdom also told people it’s okay to abuse slaves, slaughter Jews and eat the flesh of animals. For every piece of advice, there’s a counter-adage that might be equally valid.</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.” &lt;–&gt; “There are no wrong notes in jazz.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.” &lt;–&gt; ““Be yourself!”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.” &lt;–&gt; “Be in the moment!”</li> </ul> <p>Vegetarians and animal activists know this conflict intimately. How often have you been invited to eat a piece of meat, and feel like you “should” out of courtesy or politeness – but also feel like you “shouldn’t” perpetuate violence against innocent creatures.</p> <p>It’s up to all of us to decide how much we follow social convention, and how much we exert our own agency. Expressing myself through my choices typically brings me join, and so here are a few ways I like to do it:</p> <ul> <li>Arranging your living environment to be tidier.</li> <li>Choosing to focus on your breath.</li> <li>Brushing your teeth, or flossing to satisfaction.</li> <li>Installing Linux. I did this recently – It brings me great joy. *So* much better than Windows. It feels like I have a whole new computer. And there’s so much more choice and freedom on my laptop, now, which I had very little of on Windows.</li> <li>Wearing clothes you like, or thrifting for nice stuff.</li> <li>Creating art or music without thinking of whether it sounds “good”.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Travel</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Travel"/><published>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <ul> <li><strong>See many perspectives.</strong> While traveling I met a young Israeli sniper on the beaches of Siargao, Chinese nationalists who argue passionately in defense of the Chinese system, conservative French people who hate social welfare but also use it to travel. Keeping cool, curious, and empathetic is hard when you have different beliefs to someone.</li> <li><strong>Overcome social anxiety.</strong> So often when traveling, asking the nearest person is the best way to get the most accurate information. It’s essentially a necessity to be bold enough to do this. I think I’m relatively good at doing this but I still have reluctance sometimes that doesn’t serve me. Talking to a stranger is a subclass of “jumping into cold water” – doing something you know has to be done, but you dread and keep procrastinating. I can think of many things that induce a similar feeling: quitting a job, packing up your things, breaking up with someone.</li> <li><strong>See different societies and how they differ.</strong> Even between Thailand, Laos, and Vietnam, there were vastly different languages and governmental systems. I learned about Laotian government incompetence; Vietnamese national pride (so many communist flags!); and the laissez-faire Thai labor economy.</li> <li><strong>Learn what is essential to carry.</strong> My friend Dean brought a yoga block (like a styrofoam brick) that he used for meditation and sitting when the ground is uncomfortable. Surprisingly useful! I brought ziploc bags with me to label my things. And a nail clipper. Know thyself.</li> <li><strong>How to make choices with little information.</strong> This is so crucial. So crucial. Where is this bus going? Should I trust this tuk-tuk driver to take me to the ferry port? Why is there a “terminal fee” when I’ve already bought a boat ticket? Will my bag be overweight or just right? Is this vegetarian soup also vegan? So many cases of not knowing the full story – having to go by someone’s word and just laughing along. On the internet and in America we live in a high-information environment. You can look up anything. It is much harder to look up specifics of traveling in certain places abroad (especially in China – that’s like a whole other universe). So we rely on incomplete information. We pray to the travel gods when we have done all we can. We know that things will be okay so long as you have your passport and wallet and your life.</li> <li><strong>How to be kind to people under duress.</strong> Lack of sleep, 14-hour bus journeys, decision fatigue, tired of looking up vegan food. But then it’s always better to be nice to the next person you cross paths with. Patience under fire.</li> <li><strong>How to stay calm.</strong> Deep, slow belly breaths. There’s a book about it.</li> <li><strong>How to get information from people, and know what information sources to trust.</strong> Asking people where they recommend to go in a city. Deducing their vibe, thinking about whether you’ll like what they like. Chumming up with people, appreciating them when they help you out. Knowing people’s love languages – though most of what I give is kind words and hostel fees. Much more art than science.</li> <li><strong>Make plans that are specific but also flexible.</strong> I realized early on that having a hostel booked for at least one night is a good bet. Otherwise, remain flexible!</li> <li><strong>Adjust plans when necessary.</strong></li> <li><strong>Be in touch with your feelings about physical environments and people.</strong> Recognizing when you’re not vibing with a place and want to move on. Recognizing when the crew you’re with is not your crew, and you should kindly excuse yourself.</li> <li><strong>Communicate without a shared language.</strong> Smiles. Pointing. Gesturing. Extensive Google Translate.</li> <li><strong>Express gratitude.</strong> Traveling with just ten kilograms on your back, gratitude is often all you can give.</li> <li><strong>Self-advocate, ask for what you need.</strong> Even when someone’s paid to help you, like a hostel front desk staff, asking for something you need is difficult. And it is tiresome to always be reliant on someone else – but, well, that’s life. I hope one day I can pay this forward, and help others who rely on me.</li> <li><strong>Appreciate where you’re at.</strong> We travel the external world to explore our inner worlds. The most beautiful places can be so difficult if you’re not feeling it. Conversely, the raunchiest places can be hilarious and beautiful if you are appreciating it.</li> <li><strong>Mental endurance, persistence.</strong> All the things I mentioned above are harder when it’s month 3 or 4 of traveling.</li> <li><strong>The courage to go against the grain.</strong> When I was traveling, I had just one good friend, Dean, who was doing so at the same time. Long-term backpacking is not something most people do. The tenacity and courage it takes to do it is substantial. It also takes courage, I say to myself, to not have a job lined up, and hope that things will work out in the end.</li> <li><strong>Make trade-offs: money, comfort, time, safety.</strong> Decisions, decisions. So many of them while traveling. No routines, only moving forward. Exhausting!</li> <li><strong>How to kill time/wait when you need to.</strong> Talking to people. Reading my Kindle. Podcasts.</li> <li><strong>Ground yourself in a new physical environment.</strong> (e.g. via routine, exercise, putting luggage in a certain way). No routines but mini-routines. I had my bags set up so they felt familiar. A place for everything, and everything in its place, my dad likes to say. In the same vein, mini-routines in the morning, or a set time to go foraging for food, or having a hot beverage.</li> <li><strong>Accepting there will be mistakes.</strong> In Hong Kong, I thought it was way too pricey and bought too many groceries. I lost my hat and never went back to look for it. I got overcharged for a train booking. Mistakes are human, and I am human. It is part of life to make missteps, and these missteps do not define you. That’s a tough lesson.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">blogging in collaboration</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="blogging in collaboration"/><published>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>I want to say that I don’t write blog posts with AI. I say that, while also thinking that there may be good reasons to. And I may try it in the future. Here are some points for using AI and counter-point, too.</p> <p>Point:</p> <ul> <li>When a director “creates” a movie, they do not create it individually. The director provides the creative direction, importantly <em>chooses</em> what goes in the final cut. Yet it is actors, editors, writers and producers that do the day-to-day work to make it happen. I might write a blog post with AI in the same way that a director creates a movie. Doesn’t that have artistic validity?</li> <li>Sometimes something is just a fraction of an idea, but I’d need help/motivation to turn that into a full piece. Oftentimes examples and structure can help flesh out the idea to the reader. For instance, I had an idea, “solo travel is like joining the Jesuits”. I felt like it had legs, but didn’t know enough to really make the argument. AI stepped in in that moment.</li> </ul> <p>Counterpoint:</p> <ul> <li>Using AI to write doesn’t let you practice writing. Why is writing an important skill? It is the intentionality of words, the careful selection of language to put on a piece of paper. Writing is a way to essentialize yourself. Your written work is a textual manifestation of yourself. <ul> <li>Counter-counterpoint: Can’t writers that collaborate with AI have their own personal mark? Directors of movies are assisted, but they have their own distinctive style. I wonder how much artistry and uniqueness there is to ordering about AI in the way that exactly works for you.</li> </ul> </li> <li>It encourages the creation of junk. The author doesn’t have to put in so much effort into creation, and so that which is created is less thought-out. Of course, you can be a thoughtful, careful collaborator with AI so that you only say what you mean. You can also be a thoughtless, careless writer even without AI.</li> <li>It completes your thoughts. Perhaps a continuation of Counterpoint #1. When I’m writing, I’m forced to exactly think what I want to say. It is a certain way of looking at yourself. When AI completes your statements, it may not be an exact reflection of what is on your mind. But you may roll with it anyways. <ul> <li>Additional thought: AI is genuinely a useful thought partner. I can have a discussion with AI and learn a lot. It can take an idea or theory I have and strengthen it greatly. Still, this point stands in the sense that I believe it’s important to have sovereignty over thinking, to have a space where your thought stand independently from external forces.</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the morning after</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the morning after"/><published>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>The Republicans have taken the Senate, likely the house, and the Presidency. The legislative trifecta allows Trump to be unchallenged in the White House. What do we take from this moment?</p> <p>We cannot run history again. So we will not know the exact combination of factors that led to such a stunning defeat on the Democrats part. That said, we can wager some guesses. Kamala was female, and a black woman. As with all firsts, she needed to be exceptional. Obama met that bar – he defied the odds and won overwhelingly in 2008. Hillary didn’t. Kamala didn’t.</p> <p>What was it about Kamala that threw people off? She was left in a bad position. She had to defend Biden’s administration but also claim to be a departure from it. Her own policy record is wishy-washy. And her own agenda was amorphous. An uninspring economic agenda, no clear stance on immigration. Unconvincing stance on Israel. What geniuses told her to run this way? If this election was truly a fight against fascism, then why didn’t they try harder?</p> <p>Let’s not forget the Democrats unrelenting focus on the Donald. This is a through line between Biden and Harris’s campaigns. The focus was always, always on Donald Trump: the way he was a threat to democracy, a threat to women’s rights, a racist. As we see the results of the popular vote, I have to wonder if this rhetoric is self-defeating. Clearly, a good portion of the country has a great deal of respect for Donald Trump. And still the Democrats beat him over the head with labels. The party with the alleged moral high ground used name-calling and exagerration to fight Trump.</p> <p>This way of talking may alienate even further Trump’s base. Middle-class, working white men are the classic supporters of Donald Trump; the communities described in JD Vance’s A Hillbilly Elegy. Does it work to attack such people? If Joe Biden won on this platform in 2020, I believe it is because of his strong record of a middle of the road politician, and identity as a literal average Joe.</p> <p>Kamala was unknown by most voters before her own campaign, and so would’ve done better to define herself on positive qualities rather than “prosecuting” her opponent. Perhaps these issues could have been fixed if, like Ezra Klein suggests, we had a full-blown primary runoff for the Democratic candidate – a chance to test their nettle, show the stuff they’re made of.</p> <p>America has chosen Trump, and this is the time to find out why.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">judgement</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="judgement"/><published>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>Many people in my life have called me judgmental. The truth is that I speak my mind a lot, and sometimes people don’t like it. Judgement is seen as something that is bad and I’ve never understood this. So this blogpost aims to breakdown the stages of judgement.</p> <p>Let’s say you are a doctor working with a diabetes patient. The patient has been diabetic for a long time, and you notice they continue to eat sugary foods and drinks being told it will lead to more diabetes. That is stage 1 of judgement: observation and evaluation. The doctor observes may predict that the patient will continue to eat sugar if they continue on the current path.</p> <p>Stage 2 is about the doctor’s inner world. What does the doctor think of this person? Do they think they are a bad person? Lazy? Un-attending to their health? The subjective term “lazy” is commonly seen as a negative critique of another person. You are bad, I am good.</p> <p>Stage 3 is about expressing the inner world. Does the doctor give subtle cues that they think the patient is a bad person? Do they tsk tsk when they hear how much Coca Cola the patient has been drinking? Do they directly <em>say</em> the person is lazy, through tone of speech, imply they are bad person?</p> <p>So now let me evaluate what I think of these stages.</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1 of judgement, observation, I believe is a normal, healthy thing for human beings to do. In this case, it is the doctor’s job to have an understanding of the patient and their behaviors. Not making this evaluation would be irresponsible. Even other people in the patient’s life may have noticed their sugar-eating habits. For instance, if you look at someone who is obese, you will know so immediately and you cannot avoid it.</li> <li>Stage 2 of judgement is subjective internal criticism. I believe this is something to be avoided. There are no wrong notes in jazz (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/the-spirit-of-jazz.html">here</a>). If you believe life is a sandbox game, then you should also believe that people are entitled to lead the lives they want to lead. If someone wants to ingest sugar, tobacco, or other drugs, or pursue an unconventional life path, I believe that’s their decision – what you do in life, I believe, is an aesthetic choice. At the same time, I frequently, involuntarily, have internal subjective criticisms of others. It is natural. There are institutions at work that promote certain values over others, and we are but mere mammals socially programmed to uphold social conventions. You cannot control the thoughts you have, but you can control what you do with them.</li> <li>Stage 3 of judgement is sharing. When someone goes to see a doctor, they are probably hoping for the doctor’s objective assessment of how they’re doing in managing diabetes. Insofar as this will be positively received, it’s good. If the person legitimately needs a reminder that they should get back on the train of diabetes for the good of their health, then they will appreciate the doctor’s objective evaluation and take it seriously: something needs to change. However, what if the doctor’s objective evaluation is tinged with subjective criticism? This may in fact add to the strength of the feedback. Like parents forcing their child to practice piano or look both ways when crossing the road. However, there’s a potential issue with sharing negative critique: it isn’t inspiring. It may make the patient stressed and/or strain the relationship with their doctor. They may not want to come back for more visits in the future, in which case sharing internal critiques, even non-verbally, caused more harm than good.</li> </ul> <p>So to reiterate, judgement has three stages:</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1: Objective observation/assessment. Sometimes helpful.</li> <li>Stage 2: Subjective internal criticism. Often harmful.</li> <li>Stage 3: Sharing observations/criticism. A fine line!</li> </ul> <p>Stage 3 is by far the thorniest part of this. Ideally, when you have a beneficial, objective observation of someone, you can share it to their listening ears. But how do you know that when you share your observation, it is not tinged with your subconscious judgement of their behavior? And even if you don’t have subjective internal criticisms, will the other person understand that you are simply trying to share an objective statement? Intent of non-judgement may have a judgmental impact.</p> <p>Those who speak their mind too much are called judgmental, presumptuous, or bigoted. Simultaneously, they have the courage to share personal truths that people may appreciate. A prime example is Donald Trump. He is someone who certainly is bigoted and arrogant and over-shares. And yes, he is also speaking to concerns people have: concerns about crime, immigrants, woke culture. Personally, I am grateful for Trump, because without him we wouldn’t have known about the division that ails this country. Of course, in illuminating this he has spread discord and violence as well.</p> <p>I tell friends I love them dearly, and I tell them that certain behaviors of theirs piss me off beyond belief. I’ve sent letters to teachers and professors telling them how much their class means to mean, and when I feel like their class is meaningless. All the times I am speaking a truth I feel, and to do so is intrinsically good. Yet I realize that such truth must be tempered with compassion and tactful delivery. I don’t pretend I do a good job at this. But, for now, I do what I do and it’s a process of learning.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the spirit of jazz</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the spirit of jazz"/><published>2024-11-04T22:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T22:55:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>Every jazz musician has heard the phrase, “there are no wrong notes in jazz.” Trite but interesting, right? It implies that by definition, jazz is an artform in which there is no structure, no rules, nothing bad and nothing good. It just is. What you play just <em>is</em>.</p> <p>I mentioned this to my friend Leon and he had quite the strong reaction. He said, “I hate that statement, because it sure feels like there are wrong notes in jazz.” He recounted a time when he was at a jam session at UC Jazz playing the chords on piano. There was another pianist sitting next to him, who heard Leon playing and leaned over, “hey, where are you?” Leon pointed to the right spot. “That’s funny,” the other guy said, “because you’re playing sounds like shit.”</p> <p>The spirit of jazz differs from the institution of jazz. The institution of jazz decrees right and wrong, good and bad, professionals from amateurs. My friend Chase was in a jazz class playing drums. One time, the conductor stopped the band, and shouted at him, “Hold on, Chase. The trumpet just did that lick, why didn’t you echo it?” In the spirit of jazz, there is no right or wrong, and Chase can play however he feels. In the institution of jazz, Chase didn’t follow the rule – whether intentionally or unintentionally, that’s simply wrong.</p> <p>Minecraft is a sandbox game. In Minecraft, you can mine resources, build things, fight monsters, etc. but at least when I was into the game, there was no “winning” Minecraft. There were just things you could do, like you’re a kid playing in a sandbox. The creators of Minecraft encouraged this by introducing “creative mode” (vs. survival mode) where you could be Minecraft god and simply sculpt the landscape however you wanted. Like jazz, there was no wrong way to play the game.</p> <p>Pokemon is a mostly linear game, though it has open-world elements. Pokemon gives you the illusion of choice, because after all you can choose you’re Pokemon, you can choose who to talk to and what to buy from the Pokemart. But ultimately, the designers of the Pokemon games hope you follow a linear progression: defeat Pokemon gyms one through eight, then the elite four, and become the very “best” Pokemon trainer in the world. Education is a little like this. In school, you has some degree of choice in what you learn and what you remember down the line. Still, you are expected to keep to the path and finish school in 12 years and college in 4. Those who deviate from this path (deviants) are treated as either defective (if they are slower) or advanced (if they are faster).</p> <p>There are no wrong notes in jazz because jazz is a sandbox game. In practice I believe this means having a certain humility if you are playing music with someone (or living life with someone). Their choices may be different to the choices you would make, but you must remember that you are you and they are them. My favorite musicians are those who made art personal to themselves, however they defined it: the poetry of Simon &amp; Garfunkle, the spirituality of 1960s John Coltrane, the raspy voice of Tom Waits. It sounds trite, but there are truly no wrong notes in jazz. And jazz is like Minecraft, which is like life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">speaking plainly</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-speaking-plainly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="speaking plainly"/><published>2024-11-04T01:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T01:13:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-speaking-plainly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-speaking-plainly/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>Day 2 in the US. I wake up at Leon’s house. It’s Thursday morning, and there’s a knock on the door. I look around, but Leon is in a meeting, his mother is out, and his father appears to be changing. So I take a stab and peak outside.</p> <p>An Asian-American woman named Christina is standing outside, “Hi – I’m not here at all for any political purposes but…” I wonder if she’s here for religious purposes. “I parked my car out here on this street and it got broken into. It was a hummer – I know, a gas guzzler, but I promise it’s actually my dad’s car and my car was at the repairs and so I was just using it temporarily because I would intentionally drive a hummer, but I was just wondering if you had video footage. It was just parked right outside there.”</p> <p>Christina looked visibly shook and I offered my sympathies. I also thought it quite hilarious that she felt like she needed to justify using a hummer. I really wouldn’t care all that much. She gave me her contact and I said I would pass it on.</p> <p>“Do you know why Pakistanis love to celebrate Thanksgiving?” My buddy Commentary, a hobo/peace advocate on Berkeley campus, asks. I scratch my head. “Think about it. What is Thanksgiving – what do *I* think of Thanksgiving?” he prompts. “Thanksgiving is… genocide?” I offer. You can thank my Berkeley education for that one. “Yes, and genocide of who?” “The Indians! That’s why Pakistanis love to celebrate Thanksigiving!” I chortle.</p> <p>Next to Commentary is Chris, Berkeley’s lone conservative voice. He told me about how he doesn’t like Trump, but he’s a necessary evil, and actually Chris himself is a Reagan conservative, and conservatism hasn’t changed that much since the 80s, because the conservatives are all about keeping things the same – that’s what conservative means. Commentary and Chris duke it out on campus all day, each saying radical-sounding things to students on campus. The Sproul Plaza in a way invites this, though I know most people walk straight through with AirPods on. Me talking to both Chris and Commentary was doing everyone else a service.</p> <p>I don’t know if I understood how absurdly liberal Berkeley is until this day. When I see Berkeley, San Francisco and Oakland after coming back from Taiwan, I see a bunch of people who are scared to offend, scared to make jokes, scared to talk about what they really feel for fear of judgement. There are a few exceptions, like Commentary. But I think people my age are burdened by a perfectionism when it comes to speech and ideas. A perfectionism that hinders curiosity and self-realization.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reverse Culture Shock</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-reverse-culture-shock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reverse Culture Shock"/><published>2024-11-01T17:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-01T17:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-reverse-culture-shock</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-reverse-culture-shock/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>It’s been a long long time since I got to a blog post, so let’s go ahead and do it!</p> <p>I landed in San Francisco around 11am on Wednesday. The line for immigration was extremely long, about one hour. Mostly American passport holders standing in the cue. In hindsight, I did go to the bathroom after de-boarding which probably cost me several minutes. But the important thing is that in Taiwan it wouldn’t matter. I could use the bathroom *and* get of the airport in a timely manner. Behind me a Asian-Canadian man commented, “we are just passing through, why do we have to wait so long in line!” I shrugged, powerlessly, and said, “welcome to America!”</p> <p>In the line I listened to Barack Obama’s 2004 Democratic National Convention. It sure was interesting, hearing him talk about the ideas – the ideals – that led him to get elected president. “There is no liberal America, there is no conservative America – there is only the United States of America.” That one. I reflect now that even Obama has abandoned that “abiding faith” and the “audacity of hope” for a more a more “us vs them” get-out-to-vote push against The Donald. Watching the election cycle right now is like watching a basketball match, a close one where you don’t know who’s going to win.</p> <p>I then fumbled around on the bay Area Rapid Transit. I had a precious 16 minutes to figure out how to set up a transit card in the Bay Area and connect it to a credit card. 16 minutes, because if I missed the train, there wouldn’t be another for half an hour (not so rapid, is it). Throughout the process, I worried about getting robbed on BART. I kept my belongings – essentially a whole life’s worth of possessions – close to my chest. No, honestly I didn’t have these fears when I was in college. I was cavalier about safety and perhaps rightly so, because as they say in China “you cannot avoid eating for fear of choking”. But anyways somehow the impression of America that you get in Taiwan is that it’s full of drugs, crime and robbery. The news is a dastardly place. The day-to-day reality of BART only involved two boys talking loudly in the back of the carriage (didn’t bother me, but that sort of thing doesn’t happen in Taiwan. I guess in Kaohsiung I am the equivalent of those boys).</p> <p>I crashed when I arrived at my friend Leon’s house, and when I woke up it was dark. Cold, too. Bone-shiveringly cold. Cold enough that for the first time in about 6 months, I wore shoes to go on a walk outside. Leon’s house is in Albany, a cute town close to where I went to college. It’s been about fifteen months since I’ve been somewhere so cold. My days in London seem to have been forgotten. The only thing in my mind was how freely, in-comparison, I could walk around at night in Kaohsiung. Flip flops, a key and underwear was all I needed. Although societal standards also encourage you to wear a shirt and pants.</p> <p>On my walk, I walked into a 7-Eleven. This is another past time in Taiwan; to duck out the heat, and maybe buy a carton of soy milk. American 7-Eleven was just as I remembered it: unremarkably, not so convenient. I didn’t feel moved to buy anything. But I did watch an interaction at the counter. A white guy, who reminded me of someone you’d meet at the Kaohsiung foreign bars (finally, something familiar) said “are you Seikh?” The man at the till was South Asian and said, “Seikh?” The white man continued, “Seikh. Like the religion.” The other man: “Oh, no I’m Muslim.” The white man said, “Oh, Muslims. Wow, awesome. I have a bunch of really good friends who are Muslim.”</p> <p>These anecdotes are all to say that I feel like a total Taiwanese FOB (Fresh of the Boat). America feels unwieldy, expensive, unsafe. In three days, my Taiwanese permanent residence expires, which means I don’t have any legal status in the country. I’ve said goodbye to beloved friends there. And they all wished me luck going back to my country. But now I’m here, in the great US of A, and I feel remarkably out of my comfort zone. Everything is scary, different. Thank god I speak English, and have vestigial memory of aspects of this society. But after over two years living abroad, I feel again like I have a tenuous connection to this country.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One month in China</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-07-one-month-in-china/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One month in China"/><published>2024-07-24T09:21:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T09:21:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-07-one-month-in-china</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-07-one-month-in-china/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was originally posted on blogger.</em></p> <p>I’ve been traveling in China for about a month, and have a couple weeks more in the country. Surprisingly, most people are willing to talk politics, in a large, outdoor space. It’s fascinating getting people’s opinions, and I have some of my own at the end of this post.</p> <ul> <li>A doorman in Lijiang, Yunnan calls out “hello!” to me in English. I answer in English, to the groaning of my friends who know I speak Chinese. I ask the man, “you are Japanese?” Obviously he is Chinese (it’s my idea of a joke). He says, “NOOO! I HATE JAPANESE”. He asks my friends Leon and Catherine to translate for him (they reply by telling him that I actually speak Chinese just fine). “Do you know about the Rape of Nanjing?” Then he explains that Japan fucked up China in World War II, and he hopes that America, great America, will launch another bomb on their homeland.</li> <li>On a hike, the Tiger Leaping Gorge, also in Yunnan. A man asks where I’m from, and I respond saying America in Chinese. He tells me something like this… “America is a great country. Actually, America has helped China a great deal. China was small and vulnerable before, a hundred years ago, but America lifted China up. It is to America that we owe lots of thanks. It is a pity, now, in the media environment, that the news outlets are out to criticize Japan and America. They want to paint an enemy.”</li> <li>At lunch on a group day trip. Emboldened by friends sitting nearby, I ask a man at our table: What do you think of America? “You want my honest thoughts?” <em>Yes, of course. You will get my honest thoughts in return.</em> “America is a a young, immature country. You see, China has 5,000 years of magnificent history. And the US? You have not even three hundred years.” I respond, <em>if you are going to count age, you ought to use the same way of counting for both countries. The American system of government is 250 years old, the Chinese Communist Party is only 75 years old. So that makes the US several times older than China.</em> (my American friends nod in assent). The man says, “No, I am talking about civilization. Civilization in China is 5,000 years old.” <em>I tell him, but America has a vast history of indigenous peoples. You think that is not civilized?</em></li> <li>In Chengdu, I bump into a mob of college students trying to get photos of a celebrity (Karry Wang) leaving his residence. I talk to three college seniors, engineering majors. They are quite interested in American politics, and all have VPNs so they can get around the Chinese firewall. They ask me, “Do you support Donald Trump or Joe Biden? Isn’t it hard to choose between a liar and an old man?” <em>Trump is a bigot and I don’t like him at all. I am with the Democrats.</em> “So you just hate Trump, and would vote whomever the Democrats nominate,” they say, in a nod of recognition. I say <em>basically, yes</em>. <em>Can I ask you some questions? You don’t live in a democracy. Isn’t it bad that more and more power goes to Xi Jinping? Don’t you feel like fighting back and making a truly democratic system?</em> They say, “We have a form of democracy, we have representatives, but it is not one person, one vote like in the US. However, do you have real democracy? You say you don’t want to vote for either candidate, but you are forced to choose Joe Biden. So that is the same for us and Xi Jinping. And besides, we are happy with life in China. If there were a problem, we would revolt (well, maybe not us, but someone would). The system works, so if it ain’t broke, don’t fix it.”</li> </ul> <p>I first went to China in 2019. That was a great experience, and I still have some good friends from that trip where I taught English at a summer camp, and went about for a week or two. I also went in July, 2023, by which point my Chinese had vastly improved. I also noticed certain things about China at that point: the immense proliferation of electric vehicles, the fantastic public transport systems, the safety and cleanliness of the streets.</p> <p>This trip has been my most in-depth and about what I expected. The points about transport and public spaces remain true. Additionally, I’ve noticed that cost of living is remarkably cheap, including eating nice noodle, buying fresh fruit, and staying in a hotel (for context, I’m staying in Chengdu, a city of 20 million people, in a hostel for about 6 USD a night and spend about 10 USD a day on food). Oh, and also the payment system and transport cards within cities are entirely done via. scanning a QR code with your mobile phone. This is slightly annoying, if you’re like me and don’t like getting out your phone, but it avoids frictions eg. getting change on a public bus. And it means that shops literally just need a WeChat/Alipay account and a QR code for secure transactions.</p> <p>The throughline of these strengths I believe is strong state capacity. The government in China – for all the foreign critiques – gets shit done. It builds high speed rail, it subsidizes EV, it makes housing a priority (after 1 month here, I can count the number of homeless people I’ve seen on one hand). The government (I assume) partners with companies like Alipay (which does payments and public bikes) and Didi (the Chinese Uber) and cTrip, the railway booking service. Or, these big businesses are so huge they act like public infrastructure for other businesses around the country.</p> <p>Another strength of China is the national pride. In cafes and restaurants, you hear 95% of the time Chinese Mandarin locally grown music. Chinese people seem to buy into the fiction that the CCP has created. The fiction that China is great, that there is 5,000 years of history, that democracy in America has brought havoc and school shootings, that Taiwan will join the PRC in due time. I’m skeptical of these narratives, but they bring pride and meaning for people living here. After all, most people in China are stuck being Chinese, so they might as well be happy about it. Sort of a Brave New World-esque situation.</p> <p>So in conclusion, China has a lot to admire about it. The housing and mass transit is a dream for liberal activists in the US, and I daresay there’s a lot we can learn from. I do think the nationalism and internal media landscape is a downside. But in general, the Western media landscape is certainly skewed against China, and rarely appreciates the strengths of the political system here. There should be some pressure on China to liberalize its politics, but also a healthy appreciation for what they’ve done for 1.4 billion people.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="politics"/><category term="travel"/><category term="social change"/><category term="personal"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was originally posted on blogger.]]></summary></entry></feed>