<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://tohab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rohan Prasad</title><subtitle>A place where Rohan publishes his writings and artwork. </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2020-07-21-themes-and-reflections-on-avatar-last/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2020-07-21-themes-and-reflections-on-avatar-last</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2020-07-21-themes-and-reflections-on-avatar-last/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2020/07/themes-and-reflections-on-avatar-last.html">here</a>*. <strong>Introduction</strong></p> <p><em>Avatar: The Last Airbender</em> tells of a Asiatic, fantasy world with four great nations: the Water Tribes, the Earth Kingdom, the Fire Nation and the Air Nomads. Some people in those nations can bend the elements, using their powers for good or evil. A hundred years before the show’s beginning, the Fire Nation declared war on the others and are about to finish what they started. Only the Avatar can unite all four elements and bring balance to the world.</p> <p><em>Avatar</em> is a kids’ show, but it’s not <em>just</em> a kids’ show. It’s a cinematic master-piece, with hand-drawn animation and deep references to East Asian religions and martial arts. It has a story that will blow you away. It tells of balance &amp; destiny, loss &amp; family, changing cultures, coming of age, and peace &amp; violence. Those are the themes, at least, that I will discuss here… but watching it brought about far more inspiration than I can discuss in a blog-post.</p> <p>I urge you to watch this show. After this introduction, I’ll be assuming you have… Don’t worry – you can always read my blog later. But <em>Avatar</em> cannot wait – the fate of the world lies in your hands.</p> <p><strong>Balance &amp; Destiny</strong></p> <p><em>“My grandmother used to tell me stories about the old days – a time of peace… When the Avatar kept balance between the Water Tribes, Earth Kingdom, Fire Nation and Air Nomads. But that all changed when the Fire Nation attacked.”</em></p> <p><em>– Katara, Book 1: Ep. 1</em></p> <p>Balance and Destiny are key elements of the <em>Avatar</em> story. These elements that make it a legend, rather than just an animation, in that they make the action and the cultures portrayed in a spiritual context.</p> <p>First off, there’s balance. The idea of balance probably comes from Taoism. In Taoism, there is the Yin and the Yang which represents the sun and moon or male and female. Yin and Yang is referenced directly In Book 1 Ep. 20, when the moon spirit comes down from the spirit world and takes the form of a fish – the balance is threatened when Commander Zhao captures the Moon spirit. At other times, the characters must balance the rage of warring nations, the home of spirits with fast-paced industrialization, and the elements too: fire, earth, wind, and water.</p> <p>In regards to the elements, the Fire Nation is a grand force that pushed them out of balanced. They started the war with Sozin’s Comet, an astrological moment that gave them enough power to slaughter the monks of Aang’s childhood. In these moments of destruction, the Fire Nation forgot about the balance in the world. They became consumed by their greed, and did not balance pride with compassion. They became a more powerful nation but lost a sense of themselves: their cultures, traditions, and <em>life</em>.</p> <p>We can learn from the Fire Nation’s mistake in the non-Avatar world. Here, we must balance our desires for money with our friendships; our ego with our humility; our work and our life. Wiser people than me have thought of this, so it’s better to read about Taoism and the other traditions referenced in <em>Avatar</em> before making claims. However, I do think that the lessons about <em>balance</em> that the <em>Avatar</em> seeks to create are relevant to us, too.</p> <p>Now, destiny. Take Prince Zuko, a character whose destinyis split. His great-grandfather is Fire Lord Sozin, the one who started the war. But his other great-grandfather is Avatar Roku, whose reincarnation is meant to restore balance to the nations. Poor Zuko’s life is in turmoil because of actions of his fore-fathers, and no real fault of himself. This is a theme in the novel, with characters being thrust into situations or duties that they did not ask for. Zuko spends much ofthe seriessearching his soul and trying to understand his true destiny – though this causes great anguish (much like real life: it is never easy to go against a path set by your family). His half-scarred face represents his split heritage and his undecided destiny: one side cursed but longing for the Fire Lord’s acceptance, the other side open to the creation of a new world.</p> <p>Aang, too, is burdened with responsibilities that he didn’t ask for. Everyone expects him to “bring balance to the world,” because that is what the Avatar has done for centuries. Aang is only a twelve-year-old kid, but he takes on this responsibility with great diligence. He has no other choice, after all – if that is what the Avatar has done for 10,000 years, who is he to stray from that path? That sense of destiny is what gives the series intense weight, because the balance of the elements lies on the protagonists’ shoulders. It’s also what gives us confidence in the characters, because we know that with destiny on their side, they cannot fail. As Martin Luther King Jr. said, “the arc of history bends toward justice.”</p> <p>But it is not easy to bring balance to the world. It is not done by winning one battle, jailing on bad person, or learning one element. Destiny – our duty to the world – takes a life of perseverance, reflection, and commitment. With patience (and some story-telling), Aang is able to bring balance to two warring tribes (Book 1: Ep. 11). With reflection, Aang is able to unlock his seven chakras (Book 2: Ep. 20). And with commitment, he and his friends are able to defeat the Fire Lord and his armies, when all other hopes were lost (Book 3: Ep. 20).</p> <p>For the characters in <em>Avatar</em>, it was never easy to discover their destiny, or bring balance to a world in such disarray. Goodness is never easily won. And yet, they did it. In <em>our</em> world that’s full of evils like inequality and greed, I believe it is our destiny to restore balance in any way we can.</p> <p><strong>Loss &amp; Family</strong></p> <p><em>Leaves on the vine</em></p> <p><em>Falling so slow</em></p> <p><em>Like fragile tiny shells</em></p> <p><em>Drifting in the foam</em></p> <p><em>Little soldier boy</em></p> <p><em>Come marching home</em></p> <p><em>Brave soldier boy</em></p> <p><em>Comes marching home</em></p> <p>So sings Uncle Iroh on the birthday of his lost son, Lu Ten. Iroh transformed when he lost his son. He went from being a fiercesome general – the Dragon of the West – to the kind old man who loved and mentored all. In his vignette in <em>Tales of Ba Sing Se</em>, we focus on the loss he faced in this long war. Lu Ten, in a way, symbolises the countless nameless, faceless soldiers that die in great battles. As tears flow from Iroh’s face, and his voice cracks singing his lullaby, we can sense some of the magnitude of his loss.</p> <p>Loss shaped him to be the kind soul he is, and so too did it shape Katara, daughter of Kya. Because her mother died, and her father went off to war, Katara assumes the role of a mature, responsible adult in the Southern Water Tribe. Like many others in the story, she is unwillingly thrust into adulthood because of violence a loss that occured early in life. Katara performs this role so well, but this tragedy had lasting impacts on her, too. She is as fierce as she is kind when confronted with the man who murdered her mother in the name of the Fire Nation, even using blood-bending on a suspect. Despite her ferocity, Katara has suffered tragedies. When she cries out for her dad – pleading him and Aang not to abandon her (Book 3: Ep.2)– it becomes clear that she <em>has</em> been deeply affected by losing loved ones. Part of her is still the young girl who cried out for her lost mother, and would do anything to get her back. In part, this drives her to strike out against the Fire Nation and have hope in the Avatar. But in her water-bending prowess and vast accomplishments, her loss is never forgotten.</p> <p>Finally, Zuko and Azula also face loss; not from the death of their parents, but by their rejection. Zuko is unloved and disregarded by Ozai, his cruel father. But even after banishment, a lifelong scar, and humiliation, Zuko still craves Ozai’s approval. I think this shows the way that family shaped Zuko, even with all that he went through. Raised in the Fire Nation palace, loved by his mother and admiring his father, Zuko couldn’t help but dream to be accepted by the Fire Nation and aspire to become Fire Lord. Azula, too, was born into a war-hungry, violent family. Her mother, Ursa, deemed her monstrous, which led to an exaggeration of that trait and a reluctance to grow close to anyone. Azula, like her fore-fathers in the Imperialist Fire Nation, seeks power and victory – not balance or friendship – as her teenage dream. And when this is torn from her by Zuko, and when her friends also turn on her, she is abandoned in her own mental torture.</p> <p>It’s important that <em>Avatar: The Last Airbender</em> deals with loss. It shapes the characters in ways that I can only attempt to understand. That is the legacy of war: not victory or conquest, but unimaginable grief.</p> <p><strong>Changing cultures</strong></p> <p>Few children’s shows deal with genocide, but <em>Avatar</em> tackles the topic bravely. While Aang was in the iceberg, the Fire Nation went to each Air Temple and killed the Air Nomads – the monks, children, and venerable teachers that Aang knew and loved (including Monk Gyatso, Aang’s tutor and advocate). Aang comes to know this suddenly in Book 1: Ep. 3, when he sees the remains of the Southern Air Temple. He is driven to the <em>Avatar</em> state, searching for vengeance on those who destroyed his family. How can it be, to be the sole survivor of a genocide? To be the last air-bender? How large was his guilt at being absent when the genocide happened? (Book 1: Ep. 12)</p> <p>This guilt becomes anger when Aang finds out that the NorthernAir Temple has been remade by a steam-punk group with engineered gliders (Book 1, Chap. 17). At first, Aang hates the idea of his spiritual home being used for this new purpose. His conservatism is understandable. How can these people change a culture that is on the brink of extinction? The engineers knew little of the Air Nomads, and still took over the sacred temple with no authority to do so. Eventually, Aang accepts what has happened to the temple. He understands that the engineers need a place to live, and have tried their best to imitate some Air Nomad traditions without the powers of bending. Nonetheless, it is important to give respect to communities and traditions we have built from, and respect their soveirgnity in the modernized world.</p> <p> </p> <p>As a migrant through time, Aang also experiences the change in the Fire Nation after they became an Imperialist power. In Book 3: Ep. 2, Aang goes to Fire Nation school, and learns about the false history they tell in annihilating the Air Nomad’s army (in reality, the Air Nomads were monks and had no military force). Later in that episode, he teaches his schoolmates the bright and lively dances of the old Fire Nation, letting them loose and liberating them from the oppressive education system that resembles Victorian England. Their students are brought up to be soldiers and despise the other three great civilizations. This education system was really interesting to me – it shows not only have the Fire Nation oppressed others, they have repressed their own fluorishing, creative culture.</p> <p>The Fire Nation twists their cultures in more ways than one. Prince Zuko loses his ability to fire-bend when he lets go his hatred for Aang. Previously, that hatred was what gave him – and all other fire-benders – the power to bend. So Aang and Zuko seek to re-learn fire-bending (Book 3, Ep. 12). They find theSun Warriorsand meet the last Dragons: Ran and Shaw. The Dragons take the Chinese form, with long bodies and noble whiskers, rather than the Westernized dragons seen in most American media. Ran and Shawteach Aang and Zuko the origins of fire-bending: an art with beauty and life, rather than hate and aggression. With this, Zuko’s fire-bending becomes stronger than before, and more in line with the original teachers. This story is yet another example of how the Fire Nation transformed their culture, leading with fear and oppression rather than its noble origins.</p> <p>(there’s also Avatar Day, where an Earth Nation town burns statues of the Avatars in retaliation of a former leader. This town ends up honoring Aang for saving them. This is an example of how great figures like the Avatar can change cultures).</p> <p>Cultures change constantly in our lives. Some of that can be good, but it’s worth considering when it’s not. In <em>Avatar</em>, cultures change mostly from war and conflict. In particular, this changes the fabric of the Fire Nation. Everyone born in such a culture becomes someone they are not meant to be.</p> <p><strong>Coming of age</strong></p> <p>Most of the main characters in <em>Avatar</em> are kids, and thus we see remarkable growth and maturity throughout the course of the series.</p> <p>Take Prince Zuko, a banished teenager struggling to regain his honor. He starts out angry and obsessed with hunting the Avatar. Zuko is powerful, but harbors resentment to Azula and Ozai, feeling ostracized and desperate to prove his worth. Eventually, when Zuko <em>is</em> accepted by his father and has everything he had ever wanted, he realizes that it is not the right path for him. His Uncle was right – he realizes – and Zuko decides that to be his own man, he must forge his own destiny. With this resolve Zuko confronts his father and helps Aang bring balance to the Four Nations, playing a essential role in ending the war.</p> <p>Saaka, too, is a character that grows from a Southern Water Tribe boy. He starts out cocky, ordering about the little kids in his village, but his humbled as he sees the Kyoshi Warriors and his element-bending friends. He loses a girl he loves to the heavens, and fights endlessly to save Suki from danger (not that she needed saving, anyways). His growth cumulates in Book 3, Ep. 4when he learns the Way of the Sword from Pian Dao. He spends hours painting, practicing, and meditating under this master. Such obedience would offend the proud water tribe boy, but Saaka takes it with stride. It pays off, too, as his swords-master challenges him to a duel and Saaka practically wins. His ingenuity and courage is tested many times in the series, but every time Saaka asserts himself as a valuable member of Team Avatar.</p> <p>Aang, of course, bears the burden of being the Avatar. A hundred years ago, before the Fire Nation sparked destruction, Aang’s destiny drove him to run away from the Air Nomads. He was caught in a storm of despair and longing for his old childhood (Book 1: Ep. 12). In the series, he realizes that a lot rests on his shoulders. Defeating the Fire Lord was never going to be an easy task. However, Aang’s mentors help him in facing this massive challenge. Avatar Roku helps him learn the history of the Avatar and the Fire Lord(Book 3: Ep. 6), and the powers and peril of the Avatar State. Iroh hears Aang’s desperation and advises that: “sometimes life is like this dark tunnel. You can’t always seee the light at the end of the tunnel, but if you just keep moving, you will come to a better place.” (Book 3: Ch. 19). Toph teaches Aang the strength of will and solidity that lets him become an earth-bender. Katara and Zuko teach him how to bend water and fire. And Guru Pathik helps Aang unlock his seven chakras and be free from his material possessions. These mentors help Aang face the challenges of his burdened life, a necessary component of coming of age.</p> <p>Aang’s friends help him too – especially his budding romance with Katara. Katara offers immense emotional support to Aang, helping him bear the burden of the Hundred Years War. Only Katara can coax Aang out of the Avatar State, brought by the fury at losing Appa or his Air Nomad brethren. And Katara always believes in Aang, since the very beginning of opening sequence.</p> <p>In some ways it is natural that Aang falls in love with Katara, but in other ways it’s odd because of the motherly, care-taking role that she plays in his life (Aang and Toph may have been a better choice). Nonetheless, their romance cements the support that they have for each other, a heart-warming consequence of the journey they went through.</p> <p>It’s nice to read coming of age stories. It makes young children think about their experiences and what kind of person they want to become. And it makes old people like me reflect on our adolescence and what shaped us. In <em>Avatar</em>, we see the importance of mentors, friendships, and self-determination in making us the people we want to be.</p> <p><strong>Peace and Violence</strong></p> <p><em>“You were right about what Katara needed. Violence wasn’t the answer… But I have a question for you – what are you gonna do when you face my father?”</em></p> <p><em>– Prince Zuko, Book 3: Ep. 14</em></p> <p>The interplay of peace and violence is central to the Avatar narrative. Violence is the flame that starts conflict or a transformation… until peace is called to calm the storm.</p> <p>Consider Zuko’s journey of banishment and eventual re-claiming of the Fire Lord. His journey starts with a violent tradition: the Agni Kai. This duel against his father is what scarred him, and marked his destiny to hunt the Avatar during his banishment. And, indeed, his “treason” was protesting a Fire Nation general’s decision to send innocent soldiers to die in battle. In both causes, Zuko fought violence with non-violence – maintaining his honor and showing his true self. When Zuko faces Azula in the Book 3 Finale, he must return to the violent tradition of the Agni Kai. This time, he wins, having knowledge of original fire benders, but he does not scar Azula in the same way his father scarred him. He uses violence as a means to achieving peace. And further, he risks his own life to save Katara, another selfless act that solidifies his position as a peaceful Fire Lord.</p> <p>Iroh’s transformation, too, is one from violence to peace. We see Iroh as a laid-back, tea-loving Uncle in the beginning of the series. Later, however, we find out his bloody past: his ferocity in battle, his laughter at the siege of Ba Sing Se. His culture – which Zuko shared – is one that valorizes violence and the destruction of others, and so it is natural for him to have these traits from being born into it. However, as mentioned in <em>Loss &amp; Family,</em> the death of Iroh’s son is what drives Iroh to become a peaceful man. He treats all people, no matter their nationality, as friends. He allows himself to go to Fire Nation prison to save Aang and his friends. The peace and self-sacrifice with which Iroh carries himself is the epitome of non-violence.</p> <p>Another character that battles with violence is Katara. Her commitment to non-violence is tested when Zuko helps her find the man who murdered her mother (Book 3: Ep. 14). (Katara’s mother, Kya, sacrified herself by saying she was a water bender. Another example of self-sacrifice to protect others). Katara now has power over the man who kill her mother, but decides – with Aang’s encouragement – to forgive him, rather than take vengeance. She realizes that killing a man will not bring back her mother or her childhood – it will only continue the cycle of violence. As Aang says, doing nothing is easy, but forgiving is hard. Thus the path to peace tests Katara in a way that no battle could.</p> <p>Aang and the Air Nomads are of course, non-violent till the end. Aang takes immense care of Appa and Momo, treating them like family even in the toughest conditions. When Appa is lost in Book 2, Aang cries and searches far and wide to find him again. Aang and the other Air Nomads are also devout vegetarians, showing their peaceful devotion to non-human animals and nature. And in battle, Aang avoids hurting his opponents. He dodges attacks thrown at him, and avoids striking by carefully tying up or otherwise incapacitating his opponents.</p> <p>The fate of Fire Lord Ozai is the ultimate test of Aang’s non-violence. How will he treat this man – the descendent of the people who murdered his people? A man with plans to wipe out the entire Earth Nation? Aang asks the Avatars of the past, who tell him time and time again to “be decisive” and “finish” the Fire Lord. This answer was not satisfactory for Aang. He searches his heart and the lineage of the Avatars and finds an answer: energy-bending. Instead of killing Ozai, Aang takes his fire-bending powers away from him. He ends this bloody war without a single needless death.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>You probably know why I like <em>Avatar</em> so much. There’s so much to unpack, and my blog-post only scratched the surface (some other themes: friendship, resistance, gender empowerment). Each episode has it’s own story, beautifully wrapped in a 25-minute ball of goodness. The epic-ness of the saga parallels <em>Lord of the Rings</em>, <em>Harry Potter</em>, and <em>Eragon</em> – the last two of which shaped my childhood in many ways.</p> <p>I think <em>Avatar</em> is a powerful example of how fiction can really make a difference. The lessons we learn from Aang, Katara, Zuko or Iroh inspire us to be better people and bring balance to our own lives in any way we can.</p> <h2 id="i-feel-really-grateful-that-the-show-exists-and-that-so-many-talented-people-put-time-into-writing-story-boarding-animating-music-ing-sound-tracking-and-spreading-the-message-to-kids-and-adults-across-the-world-the-lessons-of-team-avatar-will-not-be-forgotten-and-remain-dear-to-my-heart">I feel really grateful that the show exists, and that so many talented people put time into writing, story-boarding, animating, music-ing, sound-tracking, and spreading the message to kids and adults across the world. The lessons of Team Avatar will not be forgotten, and remain dear to my heart.</h2> <h2 id="1-comments-captured-from-original-post-on-blogger">1 comments captured from <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2020/07/themes-and-reflections-on-avatar-last.html">original post</a> on Blogger</h2> <p>**Unknown said on 2020-07-27** The specific, concrete examples you provided reminded me of literary analysis essays I wrote in high school. I feel your inspiration in your writing. I laughed aloud when you implied that Lord of the Rings did not shape your childhood in many ways, either because you read it later or because you found it less meaningful.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2021-02-17-pharmakon-remedy-and-poison/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2021-02-17-pharmakon-remedy-and-poison</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2021-02-17-pharmakon-remedy-and-poison/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2021/02/pharmakon-remedy-and-poison.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>I just learned about an interesting concept: “pharmakon.” The way I was taught it, this Greek word describes something that is both a medicine <em>and</em> a poison at the same time.</p> <p>How is this possible? Well, as the German physician and philosopher Paracelsus says, “everything is a poison. The difference between a poison and a remedy depends on the dose.” A notable example is Botox, a “therapy” that uses very mild doses of botulinum toxin to paralyze skin cells in one’s face and prevent wrinkling. It’s okay, though a little cringe-worthy, in small doses… but just ~2 nano-grams of botulinum toxin per kilogram of bodyweight is a lethal dose – our system simply shuts down once exposed.</p> <p><em>Pharmakon</em> is also a term in philosophy, and for good reason. I can think of countless things that are both “remedies” for society, but also a potential source of toxicity. Consider: democracy prevents dictators from ruling forever, but also allowed the rise of populism and election of Donald Trump. Private pharmaceutical companies developed the Coronavirus vaccine extraordinarily quickly, but won’t give fair prices to the Global South. Our phones allow unbelievable amounts of communication with people all around the world, but also can be addictive and fuel loneliness in society.</p> <p>It’s easy to deal with good and evil, but much harder to deal with <em>pharmakon</em>. When new technologies come up, like wearable computers or immersivevideo games, we have to watch out for the pitfalls and toxicity of it, even while recognizing the convenience and joy it may bring. That’s really difficult sometimes, but necessary for living in this complicated world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2023-01-12-swimming-with-fishes-or-my-english-is/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T04:40:13+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2023-01-12-swimming-with-fishes-or-my-english-is</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2025/2023-01-12-swimming-with-fishes-or-my-english-is/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2023/01/swimming-with-fishes-or-my-english-is.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>How good is my English? Really, quite good. In fact, yours is too, if you can understand every word I’ve used in my blog. I’m beginning to understand that being fluent in a language is no easy task. It took me two decades to get to my level with a sponge-like, child’s brain and a fully immersive English environment. And not to brag, but I was speaking rather fluent English by maybe age 6. From then on, my diction and sophistication has only grown.</p> <p>It sounds like a flex – but this is the case for I believe about half a billion people in the world. And for the remaining several billion, another language serves as their “mother tongue”. For the second language learner, though, learning English is a monumental task. One that even after a whole lifetime could be said to be incomplete. The second language learner doesn’t have the same intuitive grasp of diction, rhythm, or pronunciation that the native speaker is blessed with from a young age. Perhaps if they are lucky, they live in a country where English is spoken, and from can catch the thrown-about phrases from people on the streets. Yet that doesn’t mean you’ll easily learn the English used in novels, policy memos, or political manifestos – that work has to be done day-by-day for years on end. Learning a language is like trying to swim among the fishes.</p> <p>Some days it seems that learning Chinese becomes harder and harder the more I do it. Imagine a slowly expanding ball of knowledge; in the beginning, it only contains a few polite phrases (你好, 謝謝, 我是美國人); but over time, it grows and grows, and so too does its surrounding area. After long enough, it encompasses all the “conversational topics” it could ever have imagined; but the conversations get longer and longer; and its aspirations grow and grow; and it realizes that topics like the geography of Taiwan’s Jade Mountain and the pros and cons of nuclear power require their own specific set of vocabulary and fluency; and the ball wonders if attaining such mass is ever possible.</p> <p>The de facto ideal for Chinese learners is set by reknown foreign “Sinologists”. Also called “China experts”, “China hands”, or “China watchers”, these are foreign professionals that have studied Chinese for many decades and made their careers out of mastering and utilizing their proficiency in the language. Take <a href="https://youtu.be/owsRB4IKJyA">this clip</a> of Perry Link (林培瑞), a literature professor, comparing the Chinese administrations of Xi Jinping and Mao Zedong. To the untrained ear, it’s impossible to tell that he’s not a native Beijing-er (I include myself in this categorization). Yet a native Chinese speaker might tell you that his grammar has English influences, or that his “zh” or “ü” are not quite right. Another interesting example is Reverend László Ladányi, a Hungarian-born Jesuit priest (1914-1990). He specialized in interpreting the public statements of the Chinese Communist Party that was and are layeered in rich language, idioms and CCP-only allusions<strong>.</strong> László Ladányi was perhaps the only Westerner able to decipher such documents in the 1950s and 60s. Now, many more such burgeoning academics exist.</p> <p>It seems to me that each of these students of Chinese gave up a great deal to “master” the language. Language, like rocket science or brain surgery, is something anyone can do <em>if</em> they dedicate themselves to it. The more pertinent question may be – are you willing to do what it takes? It’s rather like Wormtail cutting off his arm in Harry Potter, or Voldemort carving his soul into seven pieces…  Of course, learning Chinese is hardly a torturous process. Yet its opportunity costs are real, and it’s benefits are uncertain; and certainly not as monetizable as a more practical language like C++ or Python.</p> <p>I haven’t made any horcruxes. Nor have I sprouted any gils. But you can catch me out here in Kaohsiung City, swimming with the fishes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stickers, hope and change, and bible-pusher Rohan"/><published>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T04:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/12/stickers-hope-and-change-and-bible.html">here</a>*.</p> <p><strong>Taiwanese sticker culture.</strong> It’s totally normal in Taiwan to send stickers to your friends. And your coworkers, boss, customers – whoever. When I landed in Kaohsiung for the first time, my interactions with the quarantine hotel I was staying at were mediated through LINE, the common messaging app in Taiwan &amp; Japan. Most of the time, I would type something, they would respond, and then send a sticker.So many stickers. A sticker is like a glorified emoji that moves. Or you could see it like sending a meme or a GIF. And you can also buy them. And they make stuffed animals and key-chains based on the common ones.</p> <p>Honestly, I think we need more of this in the West. As I re-acclimatize to American culture, I realize how much warmth and nuance we’re missing out in with the purely textual medium.</p> <p><strong>Hope and change.</strong> What’s something that Obama, Trump, and Bernie all have in common? They acknowledged the struggle of working people in America. Obama’s 2008 campaign, “Change we can believe in.” Bernie in 2016, “Not me, us.” (with messaging about a “political revolution”). And Trump said he would “Make America Great Again” and “drain the swamp”.</p> <p>Trump’s populist messaging struck a chord with the American people, and I hope that the Democrats take note. The Democrats came off this year as out of touch, patronizing, and fake. Yes, sure, maybe sexism and racism had something to do with it. But I think really the problem is lack of authenticity.</p> <p>Trump is authentic. He speaks his mind. He’ll say things other people are afraid to say. Given polls skew towards the Democrats, it seems like there’s a number of shy Republicans out there. Why is that? Trump is also, as it happens, a master of the media. He used two attempted assasination attempts to his great advantage. Apparently, there was some photo of him working at McDonald’s that went viral. He bought the support Elon, who – whether you like it or not – made the Republicans seem a lot cooler. And he chose a convincing, well-spoken vice-presidential candidate to add in the mix.</p> <p>I do think the Democrats needed the 2024 election as a kick in the butt. If the stakes really are as high as they said, then they should be fighting a whole lot smarter. This isn’t just about more campaign dollars. The Presidential election is about picking a phenomenal candidate, and finding a message that *really* clicks with people. I sometimes feel like the Harris campaign was run in a way that made them feel satisfied with the effort they put in, but in actuality wasn’t at all competitive. Now people may disagree.</p> <p>The point is that there’s much we can learn from how the Republicans won the hearts and minds of people across the country. Without this temperature check, would we liberals have any idea how much people are hurting? People are losing their stable jobs, they’re afraid of automation and AI, and the cost of living is going up and up. This happens in fully blue states just as much as it happens in purple or red counties. So something has seriously got to change.</p> <p><strong>Bible-pusher Rohan.</strong> Before I moved to Taiwan, I was fanatical about this book, <em>The Defining Decade</em> by Meg Jay. The lessons of this book are left for another blog post. Certain books like that can really reshape my world-view. That book in particular wasn’t saying anything crazy or marvelous, but rather putting oft-repeated advice in a new perspective – one that I had an easier time digesting. It galvanized me to do something different and original: move to Taiwan and be an English Teacher. My thoughts at the time were would give me “identity capital”: a story, a set of experiences that make me a memorable human being. At the very least, it’s evidence that I can go against the grain, and follow through on something off the beaten path because it makes sense to me.</p> <p>These days, I’ve been thinking about the job search. There’s a whole slew of tips and tricks online, but that doesn’t make the job search any easier. Most of the people I’ve talked to took months to get anywhere. If you think about it, most people have only ever job hunted a few times in their life. Sometimes less. So people’s experience is limited; it is by nature anecdotal. There’s some old parable about the seven blind men that try to draw an elephant. Basically, they each touch different parts of the elephant, but with such a limited scope, they can’t get the whole picture of what the creature looks like.</p> <p>Two years ago, I recommended <em>The Defining Decade</em> to anyone and everyone. Now, I have a new Bible: <em>The 2-Hour Job Search</em> by Steve Dalton. This book is more easily summarized: instead of shooting resume after resume into the black hole of job application portals, your time is better spent networking at targeting companies by informational interviews to learn about your industry. Moreover, Dalton provides explicit instructions on how to implement this strategy. No generic tips &amp; tricks – just actionable advice, based on research and his experience as a career counselor. I like this book because it flips the traditional paradigm on its head. And god, there’s a lot of vague advice for job searching, but very few people who actually know how to do it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the spectrum of agency</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the spectrum of agency"/><published>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T03:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-12-the-spectrum-of-agency/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/12/the-spectrum-of-agency.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>If you were a rich person in the 1800s, would you used cotton shirts made by slave laborers? If you were a German in the 1940s, would you used soap made by the bodies of the victims of the Holocaust? If you were alive in the 2000s, would you have eaten the flesh of dead animals.</p> <p>Agency is how much choice we exert over our lives. The answer to those three questions for most people is maybe not, but probably yes.</p> <p>Humans are designed to go along with the stream of water that is society. We are social creatures, and are generally agreeable. I think so, at least; we are more similar than we are different. If we had too much heterogeneity, there would be more social activists, perhaps, but also more serial killers, racists, and social pariahs. Like birds flying in the sky, moving with your flock is a helpful instinct. Obedience and conformity to social expectations is what lets the world run day-to-day.</p> <p>On the other hand, humans also have an innate capacity for courage, creativity, and uniqueness. These are the qualities that create social disruption, change, and innovation.</p> <p>There’s a balance to be had. Conformity helps build great, stable nations; but too many and we’re on the road to serfdom. Disruption fuels technological progress; but too much and we’re in a land of warlords feuding over power.</p> <p>Social expectations appear in more mild senses too. For instance, the idea that you should stay till the end of a concert instead of leaving halfway through. Good, or bad? Good to respect the performers. Bad because you may be driving yourself crazy. People may come on different sides of this debate, and it’s probably a case by case situation.</p> <p>Here are some other pieces of conventional wisdom:</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.”</li> </ul> <p>These are actually all good pieces of advice, I think. But who’s to say when these rules of thumb get out of hand? Conventional wisdom also told people it’s okay to abuse slaves, slaughter Jews and eat the flesh of animals. For every piece of advice, there’s a counter-adage that might be equally valid.</p> <ul> <li>“Don’t play wrong notes.” &lt;–&gt; “There are no wrong notes in jazz.”</li> <li>“Do what I tell you to do.” &lt;–&gt; ““Be yourself!”</li> <li>“Make sure you plan ahead.” &lt;–&gt; “Be in the moment!”</li> </ul> <p>Vegetarians and animal activists know this conflict intimately. How often have you been invited to eat a piece of meat, and feel like you “should” out of courtesy or politeness – but also feel like you “shouldn’t” perpetuate violence against innocent creatures.</p> <p>It’s up to all of us to decide how much we follow social convention, and how much we exert our own agency. Expressing myself through my choices typically brings me join, and so here are a few ways I like to do it:</p> <ul> <li>Arranging your living environment to be tidier.</li> <li>Choosing to focus on your breath.</li> <li>Brushing your teeth, or flossing to satisfaction.</li> <li>Installing Linux. I did this recently – It brings me great joy. *So* much better than Windows. It feels like I have a whole new computer. And there’s so much more choice and freedom on my laptop, now, which I had very little of on Windows.</li> <li>Wearing clothes you like, or thrifting for nice stuff.</li> <li>Creating art or music without thinking of whether it sounds “good”.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Travel</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Travel"/><published>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T04:26:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-lessons-from-travel/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/lessons-from-travel.html">here</a>*.</p> <ul> <li><strong>See many perspectives.</strong> While traveling I met a young Israeli sniper on the beaches of Siargao, Chinese nationalists who argue passionately in defense of the Chinese system, conservative French people who hate social welfare but also use it to travel. Keeping cool, curious, and empathetic is hard when you have different beliefs to someone.</li> <li><strong>Overcome social anxiety.</strong> So often when traveling, asking the nearest person is the best way to get the most accurate information. It’s essentially a necessity to be bold enough to do this. I think I’m relatively good at doing this but I still have reluctance sometimes that doesn’t serve me. Talking to a stranger is a subclass of “jumping into cold water” – doing something you know has to be done, but you dread and keep procrastinating. I can think of many things that induce a similar feeling: quitting a job, packing up your things, breaking up with someone.</li> <li><strong>See different societies and how they differ.</strong> Even between Thailand, Laos, and Vietnam, there were vastly different languages and governmental systems. I learned about Laotian government incompetence; Vietnamese national pride (so many communist flags!); and the laissez-faire Thai labor economy.</li> <li><strong>Learn what is essential to carry.</strong> My friend Dean brought a yoga block (like a styrofoam brick) that he used for meditation and sitting when the ground is uncomfortable. Surprisingly useful! I brought ziploc bags with me to label my things. And a nail clipper. Know thyself.</li> <li><strong>How to make choices with little information.</strong> This is so crucial. So crucial. Where is this bus going? Should I trust this tuk-tuk driver to take me to the ferry port? Why is there a “terminal fee” when I’ve already bought a boat ticket? Will my bag be overweight or just right? Is this vegetarian soup also vegan? So many cases of not knowing the full story – having to go by someone’s word and just laughing along. On the internet and in America we live in a high-information environment. You can look up anything. It is much harder to look up specifics of traveling in certain places abroad (especially in China – that’s like a whole other universe). So we rely on incomplete information. We pray to the travel gods when we have done all we can. We know that things will be okay so long as you have your passport and wallet and your life.</li> <li><strong>How to be kind to people under duress.</strong> Lack of sleep, 14-hour bus journeys, decision fatigue, tired of looking up vegan food. But then it’s always better to be nice to the next person you cross paths with. Patience under fire.</li> <li><strong>How to stay calm.</strong> Deep, slow belly breaths. There’s a book about it.</li> <li><strong>How to get information from people, and know what information sources to trust.</strong> Asking people where they recommend to go in a city. Deducing their vibe, thinking about whether you’ll like what they like. Chumming up with people, appreciating them when they help you out. Knowing people’s love languages – though most of what I give is kind words and hostel fees. Much more art than science.</li> <li><strong>Make plans that are specific but also flexible.</strong> I realized early on that having a hostel booked for at least one night is a good bet. Otherwise, remain flexible!</li> <li><strong>Adjust plans when necessary.</strong></li> <li><strong>Be in touch with your feelings about physical environments and people.</strong> Recognizing when you’re not vibing with a place and want to move on. Recognizing when the crew you’re with is not your crew, and you should kindly excuse yourself.</li> <li><strong>Communicate without a shared language.</strong> Smiles. Pointing. Gesturing. Extensive Google Translate.</li> <li><strong>Express gratitude.</strong> Traveling with just ten kilograms on your back, gratitude is often all you can give.</li> <li><strong>Self-advocate, ask for what you need.</strong> Even when someone’s paid to help you, like a hostel front desk staff, asking for something you need is difficult. And it is tiresome to always be reliant on someone else – but, well, that’s life. I hope one day I can pay this forward, and help others who rely on me.</li> <li><strong>Appreciate where you’re at.</strong> We travel the external world to explore our inner worlds. The most beautiful places can be so difficult if you’re not feeling it. Conversely, the raunchiest places can be hilarious and beautiful if you are appreciating it.</li> <li><strong>Mental endurance, persistence.</strong> All the things I mentioned above are harder when it’s month 3 or 4 of traveling.</li> <li><strong>The courage to go against the grain.</strong> When I was traveling, I had just one good friend, Dean, who was doing so at the same time. Long-term backpacking is not something most people do. The tenacity and courage it takes to do it is substantial. It also takes courage, I say to myself, to not have a job lined up, and hope that things will work out in the end.</li> <li><strong>Make trade-offs: money, comfort, time, safety.</strong> Decisions, decisions. So many of them while traveling. No routines, only moving forward. Exhausting!</li> <li><strong>How to kill time/wait when you need to.</strong> Talking to people. Reading my Kindle. Podcasts.</li> <li><strong>Ground yourself in a new physical environment.</strong> (e.g. via routine, exercise, putting luggage in a certain way). No routines but mini-routines. I had my bags set up so they felt familiar. A place for everything, and everything in its place, my dad likes to say. In the same vein, mini-routines in the morning, or a set time to go foraging for food, or having a hot beverage.</li> <li><strong>Accepting there will be mistakes.</strong> In Hong Kong, I thought it was way too pricey and bought too many groceries. I lost my hat and never went back to look for it. I got overcharged for a train booking. Mistakes are human, and I am human. It is part of life to make missteps, and these missteps do not define you. That’s a tough lesson.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">blogging in collaboration</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="blogging in collaboration"/><published>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-blogging-in-collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/blogging-in-collaboration.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>I want to say that I don’t write blog posts with AI. I say that, while also thinking that there may be good reasons to. And I may try it in the future. Here are some points for using AI and counter-point, too.</p> <p>Point:</p> <ul> <li>When a director “creates” a movie, they do not create it individually. The director provides the creative direction, importantly <em>chooses</em> what goes in the final cut. Yet it is actors, editors, writers and producers that do the day-to-day work to make it happen. I might write a blog post with AI in the same way that a director creates a movie. Doesn’t that have artistic validity?</li> <li>Sometimes something is just a fraction of an idea, but I’d need help/motivation to turn that into a full piece. Oftentimes examples and structure can help flesh out the idea to the reader. For instance, I had an idea, “solo travel is like joining the Jesuits”. I felt like it had legs, but didn’t know enough to really make the argument. AI stepped in in that moment.</li> </ul> <p>Counterpoint:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Using AI to write doesn’t let you practice writing. Why is writing an important skill? It is the intentionality of words, the careful selection of language to put on a piece of paper. Writing is a way to essentialize yourself. Your written work is a textual manifestation of yourself.</p> </li> <li> <p>Counter-counterpoint: Can’t writers that collaborate with AI have their own personal mark? Directors of movies are assisted, but they have their own distinctive style. I wonder how much artistry and uniqueness there is to ordering about AI in the way that exactly works for you.</p> </li> <li>It encourages the creation of junk. The author doesn’t have to put in so much effort into creation, and so that which is created is less thought-out. Of course, you can be a thoughtful, careful collaborator with AI so that you only say what you mean. You can also be a thoughtless, careless writer even without AI.</li> <li> <p>It completes your thoughts. Perhaps a continuation of Counterpoint #1. When I’m writing, I’m forced to exactly think what I want to say. It is a certain way of looking at yourself. When AI completes your statements, it may not be an exact reflection of what is on your mind. But you may roll with it anyways.</p> </li> <li>Additional thought: AI is genuinely a useful thought partner. I can have a discussion with AI and learn a lot. It can take an idea or theory I have and strengthen it greatly. Still, this point stands in the sense that I believe it’s important to have sovereignty over thinking, to have a space where your thought stand independently from external forces.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the morning after</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the morning after"/><published>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T19:22:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-morning-after/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/the-morning-after.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>The Republicans have taken the Senate, likely the house, and the Presidency. The legislative trifecta allows Trump to be unchallenged in the White House. What do we take from this moment?</p> <p>We cannot run history again. So we will not know the exact combination of factors that led to such a stunning defeat on the Democrats part. That said, we can wager some guesses. Kamala was female, and a black woman. As with all firsts, she needed to be exceptional. Obama met that bar – he defied the odds and won overwhelingly in 2008. Hillary didn’t. Kamala didn’t.</p> <p>What was it about Kamala that threw people off? She was left in a bad position. She had to defend Biden’s administration but also claim to be a departure from it. Her own policy record is wishy-washy. And her own agenda was amorphous. An uninspring economic agenda, no clear stance on immigration. Unconvincing stance on Israel. What geniuses told her to run this way? If this election was truly a fight against fascism, then why didn’t they try harder?</p> <p>Let’s not forget the Democrats unrelenting focus on the Donald. This is a through line between Biden and Harris’s campaigns. The focus was always, always on Donald Trump: the way he was a threat to democracy, a threat to women’s rights, a racist. As we see the results of the popular vote, I have to wonder if this rhetoric is self-defeating. Clearly, a good portion of the country has a great deal of respect for Donald Trump. And still the Democrats beat him over the head with labels. The party with the alleged moral high ground used name-calling and exagerration to fight Trump.</p> <p>This way of talking may alienate even further Trump’s base. Middle-class, working white men are the classic supporters of Donald Trump; the communities described in JD Vance’s A Hillbilly Elegy. Does it work to attack such people? If Joe Biden won on this platform in 2020, I believe it is because of his strong record of a middle of the road politician, and identity as a literal average Joe.</p> <p>Kamala was unknown by most voters before her own campaign, and so would’ve done better to define herself on positive qualities rather than “prosecuting” her opponent. Perhaps these issues could have been fixed if, like Ezra Klein suggests, we had a full-blown primary runoff for the Democratic candidate – a chance to test their nettle, show the stuff they’re made of.</p> <p>America has chosen Trump, and this is the time to find out why.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">judgement</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="judgement"/><published>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T23:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-judgement/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/judgement.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>Many people in my life have called me judgmental. The truth is that I speak my mind a lot, and sometimes people don’t like it. Judgement is seen as something that is bad and I’ve never understood this. So this blogpost aims to breakdown the stages of judgement.</p> <p>Let’s say you are a doctor working with a diabetes patient. The patient has been diabetic for a long time, and you notice they continue to eat sugary foods and drinks being told it will lead to more diabetes. That is stage 1 of judgement: observation and evaluation. The doctor observes may predict that the patient will continue to eat sugar if they continue on the current path.</p> <p>Stage 2 is about the doctor’s inner world. What does the doctor think of this person? Do they think they are a bad person? Lazy? Un-attending to their health? The subjective term “lazy” is commonly seen as a negative critique of another person. You are bad, I am good.</p> <p>Stage 3 is about expressing the inner world. Does the doctor give subtle cues that they think the patient is a bad person? Do they tsk tsk when they hear how much Coca Cola the patient has been drinking? Do they directly <em>say</em> the person is lazy, through tone of speech, imply they are bad person?</p> <p>So now let me evaluate what I think of these stages.</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1 of judgement, observation, I believe is a normal, healthy thing for human beings to do. In this case, it is the doctor’s job to have an understanding of the patient and their behaviors. Not making this evaluation would be irresponsible. Even other people in the patient’s life may have noticed their sugar-eating habits. For instance, if you look at someone who is obese, you will know so immediately and you cannot avoid it.</li> <li>Stage 2 of judgement is subjective internal criticism. I believe this is something to be avoided. There are no wrong notes in jazz (see <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/the-spirit-of-jazz.html">here</a>). If you believe life is a sandbox game, then you should also believe that people are entitled to lead the lives they want to lead. If someone wants to ingest sugar, tobacco, or other drugs, or pursue an unconventional life path, I believe that’s their decision – what you do in life, I believe, is an aesthetic choice. At the same time, I frequently, involuntarily, have internal subjective criticisms of others. It is natural. There are institutions at work that promote certain values over others, and we are but mere mammals socially programmed to uphold social conventions. You cannot control the thoughts you have, but you can control what you do with them.</li> <li>Stage 3 of judgement is sharing. When someone goes to see a doctor, they are probably hoping for the doctor’s objective assessment of how they’re doing in managing diabetes. Insofar as this will be positively received, it’s good. If the person legitimately needs a reminder that they should get back on the train of diabetes for the good of their health, then they will appreciate the doctor’s objective evaluation and take it seriously: something needs to change. However, what if the doctor’s objective evaluation is tinged with subjective criticism? This may in fact add to the strength of the feedback. Like parents forcing their child to practice piano or look both ways when crossing the road. However, there’s a potential issue with sharing negative critique: it isn’t inspiring. It may make the patient stressed and/or strain the relationship with their doctor. They may not want to come back for more visits in the future, in which case sharing internal critiques, even non-verbally, caused more harm than good.</li> </ul> <p>So to reiterate, judgement has three stages:</p> <ul> <li>Stage 1: Objective observation/assessment. Sometimes helpful.</li> <li>Stage 2: Subjective internal criticism. Often harmful.</li> <li>Stage 3: Sharing observations/criticism. A fine line!</li> </ul> <p>Stage 3 is by far the thorniest part of this. Ideally, when you have a beneficial, objective observation of someone, you can share it to their listening ears. But how do you know that when you share your observation, it is not tinged with your subconscious judgement of their behavior? And even if you don’t have subjective internal criticisms, will the other person understand that you are simply trying to share an objective statement? Intent of non-judgement may have a judgmental impact.</p> <p>Those who speak their mind too much are called judgmental, presumptuous, or bigoted. Simultaneously, they have the courage to share personal truths that people may appreciate. A prime example is Donald Trump. He is someone who certainly is bigoted and arrogant and over-shares. And yes, he is also speaking to concerns people have: concerns about crime, immigrants, woke culture. Personally, I am grateful for Trump, because without him we wouldn’t have known about the division that ails this country. Of course, in illuminating this he has spread discord and violence as well.</p> <p>I tell friends I love them dearly, and I tell them that certain behaviors of theirs piss me off beyond belief. I’ve sent letters to teachers and professors telling them how much their class means to mean, and when I feel like their class is meaningless. All the times I am speaking a truth I feel, and to do so is intrinsically good. Yet I realize that such truth must be tempered with compassion and tactful delivery. I don’t pretend I do a good job at this. But, for now, I do what I do and it’s a process of learning.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the spirit of jazz</title><link href="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the spirit of jazz"/><published>2024-11-04T22:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T22:55:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tohab.github.io/blog/2024/2024-11-the-spirit-of-jazz/"><![CDATA[<p>*This was originally posted on blogger <a href="https://www.rohanprasad.org/2024/11/the-spirit-of-jazz.html">here</a>*.</p> <p>Every jazz musician has heard the phrase, “there are no wrong notes in jazz.” Trite but interesting, right? It implies that by definition, jazz is an artform in which there is no structure, no rules, nothing bad and nothing good. It just is. What you play just <em>is</em>.</p> <p>I mentioned this to my friend Leon and he had quite the strong reaction. He said, “I hate that statement, because it sure feels like there are wrong notes in jazz.” He recounted a time when he was at a jam session at UC Jazz playing the chords on piano. There was another pianist sitting next to him, who heard Leon playing and leaned over, “hey, where are you?” Leon pointed to the right spot. “That’s funny,” the other guy said, “because you’re playing sounds like shit.”</p> <p>The spirit of jazz differs from the institution of jazz. The institution of jazz decrees right and wrong, good and bad, professionals from amateurs. My friend Chase was in a jazz class playing drums. One time, the conductor stopped the band, and shouted at him, “Hold on, Chase. The trumpet just did that lick, why didn’t you echo it?” In the spirit of jazz, there is no right or wrong, and Chase can play however he feels. In the institution of jazz, Chase didn’t follow the rule – whether intentionally or unintentionally, that’s simply wrong.</p> <p>Minecraft is a sandbox game. In Minecraft, you can mine resources, build things, fight monsters, etc. but at least when I was into the game, there was no “winning” Minecraft. There were just things you could do, like you’re a kid playing in a sandbox. The creators of Minecraft encouraged this by introducing “creative mode” (vs. survival mode) where you could be Minecraft god and simply sculpt the landscape however you wanted. Like jazz, there was no wrong way to play the game.</p> <p>Pokemon is a mostly linear game, though it has open-world elements. Pokemon gives you the illusion of choice, because after all you can choose you’re Pokemon, you can choose who to talk to and what to buy from the Pokemart. But ultimately, the designers of the Pokemon games hope you follow a linear progression: defeat Pokemon gyms one through eight, then the elite four, and become the very “best” Pokemon trainer in the world. Education is a little like this. In school, you has some degree of choice in what you learn and what you remember down the line. Still, you are expected to keep to the path and finish school in 12 years and college in 4. Those who deviate from this path (deviants) are treated as either defective (if they are slower) or advanced (if they are faster).</p> <p>There are no wrong notes in jazz because jazz is a sandbox game. In practice I believe this means having a certain humility if you are playing music with someone (or living life with someone). Their choices may be different to the choices you would make, but you must remember that you are you and they are them. My favorite musicians are those who made art personal to themselves, however they defined it: the poetry of Simon &amp; Garfunkle, the spirituality of 1960s John Coltrane, the raspy voice of Tom Waits. It sounds trite, but there are truly no wrong notes in jazz. And jazz is like Minecraft, which is like life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008/kind#post"/><category term="legacy-blogger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*This was originally posted on blogger here*.]]></summary></entry></feed>